<hall-of-fame updated="3/14/2025">
	<inductee name="Angie Hasslinger" inducted="2019" participated="1983-1988" church="Eastside Free Methodist Church" city="Bellevue" state="WA" image="a_hasslinger.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Angie lives in Bellevue, Washington, with her husband, Glenn Hasslinger, Jr. They have a grown son, Stephen.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>The friendships made not only within my own church, but others in the quizzing program. These are some of my best friends still. It was always so fun to choose the quiz furthest away to attend, even if there were fewer teams. We were welcomed to spend the night at other quizzers' homes and get to know the quizzing families. We would stay an extra day and go to church with them before heading home. The Easter breakfasts we served to our church family as a fund raiser for Nationals were always a delight.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Romans 1:16 "I am not ashamed of the gospel, because it is the power of God for the salvation of everyone who believes: first for the Jew, then for the Gentile."</answer>
			<answer>Romans was my very first book I studied in quizzing. It was my first Quote learned. This was my favorite verse because I was often sharing with school friends and classmates Scripture in everyday conversations. I would challenge my friends to think about why we believe what we have been taught.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing encouraged me to get into God’s Word. The program offered opportunities to meet new friends from other churches. It was good to spend time learning about what Jesus and the life he had for me during the awkward teen years. I became close with my teammates and I had gratitude for all the leaders, coaches and quizmasters who encouraged me.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Quizzing introduced to me the joy of not just reading or memorizing but studying God’s word. I so enjoy when in the middle of the messy parts of life, the scriptures memorized come flooding back just at the right time. I also discovered that I enjoy encouraging others to be the Word reading and the importance of memorizing.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am serving as a quizmaster monthly as needed in the West Coast Region. I also serve in the Middle School group that meets at Timberlake Church in Redmond, Washington.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Anne Bartlett" inducted="2019" participated="1986-1989" church="Pendleton Free Methodist Church" city="Pendleton" state="OR " image="a_bartlett.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Anne Bartlett lives in Moses Lake, Washington, and is the current West Coast Regional Director for FMBQ, along with her husband, Jon. She has two sons, Tim and Joe, who are attending Seattle Pacific University.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Some highlights of my quizzing years include attending my first Nationals as a Senior Teen Rookie, traveling for the monthly quizzes, making friends at all the quizzes, and making fun of some of the intimidation tactics some teams used.</answer>
			<answer>My first Nationals sold me on Bible Quizzing. After that I put in a lot more effort and was determined to go each year that I could and compete well.</answer>
			<answer>I enjoyed traveling to the monthly quizzes since this always meant we needed to spend the night since we lived so far away from the quizzes our church didn’t host. Often we would spend the night with quizzers from the host churches, playing games, eating snacks and just getting to know one another better.</answer>
			<answer>I remember making friends at the quizzes which spanned the miles. I especially remember meeting Marvin Gray at a National competition and he was a speaker at one of our sessions. He told stories about living in the Dominican Republic. I can still remember him telling about cutting the grass with a machete instead of a mower. I, also, monthly would compete against Laura Christensen. She was the competition to beat in those days. My teammates and I would always say that she would grow up to be a lawyer since she loved to “challenge” and was good at it. Later we became co-coaches and even roommates for a short time while in college.</answer>
			<answer>I also love that I now live in Moses Lake and coach the Moses Lake Bible Quiz team. Moses Lake was a team that our team would talk about regarding their intimidation techniques for the quizzes. They dressed in button-down white shirts and ties and would stand up together and sit down together at the close of every question. They were a team of two boys who would make our team of 3 girls just laugh. Thom, one of their team members, also loved to challenge as an intimidation technique. We also predicted that he would be a lawyer someday. Sure enough, he now works for the JAG core in the army. Moving to Moses Lake I said to my husband, “I bet Mr. Neuman, the Moses Lake Bible Quiz coach, would be the church delegate who would welcome us as the new pastor to the church.” Sure enough it was. We had a great time reminiscing about the days of quizzing we shared together.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>We did not win any championships but did place 3rd at SPU in 1989.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>I Corinthians 10:13 "No temptation has overtaken you except what is common to mankind. And God is faithful; he will not let you be tempted beyond what you can bear. But when you are tempted, he will also provide a way out so that you can endure it."</answer>
			<answer>I love how it assures us that God will not let us be tempted beyond what we can handle and he will always provide a way to escape. We just have to be looking for it.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>As a teen quizzing was great for me. It helped me make friends in the new town we had just moved into. It was a great way for me to get into the word and memorize. My Dad had already had us memorizing Scripture to earn different things such as camp, ear piercings, etc., so this activity really fed into a seed that had already been planted. And I have to say I love a good competition.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I believe the difference quizzing has made in my life is to be more biblically literate than I may have ever been without quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>At our local church I serve as the financial secretary and am involved in a prayer team for the Pastor Search Committee since we are in the process of looking for a new pastor. At work, I have met with a friend and co-worker for a Bible study about once a week for the last two years.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Brian Bither" inducted="2019" participated="1997-2004" church="John Wesley FM Church" city="Indianapolis" state="IN" image="b_bither.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Brian is a pastor in a Mennonite Church in Indianapolis. In addition to preaching, teaching, visiting the sick, offering counsel, and performing the standard pastoral duties, he has gotten involved in working with immigrants in recent years, ranging from Burmese Christians who fled to the United States due to religious persecution in Myanmar to Central American immigrants living here in the United States. The common commitment to Christ and familiarity with Scripture is often the key to helping to overcome cultural, political, and even linguistic barriers.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Our trip to Quiz Finals to Seattle Pacific in 2002 was an inspiring and eye-opening experience, even though we didn’t do very well.</answer>
			<answer>Quiz Finals in 2004 was the year that our team did the best – coming in 2nd – and when I won the STV Individuals competition while my sister (Amy Bither) won the YTV individuals competition.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>2 Peter 3:9 "The Lord is not slow in keeping his promise, as some understand slowness. Instead he is patient with you, not wanting anyone to perish, but everyone to come to repentance."</answer>
			<answer>It takes some of my deepest insecurities about the apparent absence of God and claims that what "looks likerF" absence (or "slowness") is actually God’s patience. I still think this is one of the most profound and underappreciated verses in the Bible.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>First and foremost, it gave me direct knowledge of the Word of God, which was not mediated through a person or perspective but was direct. By repeating the words of Scripture regularly, it shaped my thoughts and worldview, and even my language. How many teenagers say, "By no means!"?</answer>
			<answer>It taught me how to memorize facts and process large amounts of information, which has helped me succeed in educational institutions ever since then.</answer>
			<answer>It gave me a sense of the larger Church and helped connect me to many people across the Free Methodist world, which was quite helpful in my initial pursuit of ministry.</answer>
			<answer>It was a significant point of bonding for some of my church friends and my family. Many of my cherished memories of interacting with my father in particular come from time we spent together in Bible Quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>The difference has been profound, and it’s hard to simplify it into a few answers, but here is an attempt:</answer>
			<answer>My deep familiarity with Scripture has been extremely helpful for me as a theologian, because people often make claims about the Bible or based on the Bible, and I can usually identify what Scriptures they are alluding to instantly, I can consider it in light of its broader context, or at least I can look it up and find it quickly to assess whether I agree with the claim or not. It helps me be a good “Berean” Christian.</answer>
			<answer>Knowing how to memorize and regurgitate information is still useful, and I use some Bible Quizzing tricks whenever I prepare for a sermon or need to have a large amount of information on hand in a meeting.</answer>
			<answer>I often think about Bible Quizzing as a great program that churches can start to help teenagers get connected with other people and involved in something meaningful and productive. Although several young people are over-programmed in our society, there is still a large portion of teenagers who are left to themselves, with nothing to do, and I long to get them all involved in Bible Quizzing.</answer>
			<answer>As many people say, the Scriptures “come” to you at key moments in your life as the voice of God at moments when you need to hear it. My spiritual journey has been largely shaped by the Scriptures I memorized in Quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Craig Allman" inducted="2019" participated="1984-1989" church="New Brighton Free Methodist Church" city="New Brighton" state="PA" image="c_allman.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Craig Allman lives in Ann Arbor, Michigan, with his wife, Deanna, and daughters Jenna and Emily. He serves as worship ministry for Grace Ann Arbor Church.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>The road trips were great. I loved traveling to different parts of the country for tournaments and seeing several of the Free Methodist Colleges. There were many laughing fits, water balloon attacks, and other memories made on the road. Since my parents were coaches, these trips were often our family vacations shared with the team.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Hebrews 4:12 “For the word of God is living and active. Sharper than any double-edged sword, it penetrates even to dividing soul and spirit, joints and marrow; it judges the thoughts and attitudes of the heart.” I have many favorite scriptures, but this passage connects textual word to the Living Word, Jesus Christ, and proclaims the efficacy of it all. Life will strike me to the core and this world will pass its judgment on me. But the Living Word is true, and I want to feel it bone-deep, speaking, guiding, and judging in my life.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I can’t imagine anything else giving me the motivation to memorize Scripture like Bible Quizzing did. It was not over-spiritualized. It was fun. It was camaraderie and belonging. It was also bigger than my local church and provided a connection to the larger church even beyond my denomination. Even though Bible Quizzing is in some ways a strange and unique context, it somehow connected the Scripture to the stuff of real life and to lots of relationships with real people. It gave the Scripture another dimension of credibility.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>On a deep level, the study of the gospels and letters of the New Testament gave me a doctrinal and theological foundation for leadership, discipleship, and worship in the church. Also, day to day, it is amazing what a Quote Verse can do in a crisis moment. Old hand-written quote flash cards have been tucked into journals, books, drawers and all sorts of places where I have needed to draw upon them for guidance and encouragement for myself and for others.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Glenn Hasslinger, Jr." inducted="2019" participated="1981-1985" church="Eastside Free Methodist Church" city="Bellevue" state="WA" image="g_hasslinger.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Glenn works for the Bellevue School District and serves as the Pacific Northwest Conference Director for FMBQ. He and his wife Angie have an adult son, Stephen.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>I always enjoyed the road trips we took as a quiz team. If there was a close quiz option or a farther away quiz option, we always took the one that was farther away. I know that I always wanted to spend as much time with those on my team as I could. As a result the time traveled gave us time to build relationships within our team and grow closer to God.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>No—closest we came 2nd in Young Teen Vet in 1982 and 4th in Senior Teen Vet in 1984.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Matthew 16:13-20 "But what about you?” he asked. “Who do you say I am?” Simon Peter answered, “You are the Messiah, the Son of the living God.”</answer>
			<answer> For me these verse are the simplicity of the Gospel that each one of us must choose. We all must answer for ourselves who do we say Jesus is. Simon Peter answered in the simplest form: “You are the Christ. The Son do of the living God.” There is nothing really complicated about it. When things in life get tough or the questions that may confound me arise, I am able to use these verses as a touchstone and ask as a reminder, “But what about you, Glenn ... who do you say Jesus is?” It is when I remember that he is the Christ, the Son of the living God that all the worldly complications and concerns fall away in comparison the knowledge that Jesus has got it all covered.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing was one piece of many that God had used to influence growth in my relationship with Him as a teen. It also helped me become a leader in the youth group, through the confidence I learned.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>The study I did in quizzing still guides me in what I do. The Quotes I learned come to me in situations that I face and help me make difficult decisions. The choices that have been guided by the Word that I have studied has helped me follow Jesus and I think have made my life better more full as Jesus said in John 10:10.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I have coached and quizmastered for many years. Currently besides quizzing, I am working with the middle school ministries at Timberlake Christian Fellowship.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Jon Bartlett" inducted="2019" participated="1983-1989" church="Hershey Evangelical Free Church" city="Hershey" state="PA" image="j_bartlett.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Jon Bartlett is a teacher at Moses Lake Academy in Moses Lake, Washington, where he lives with his wife Anne. He has two sons, Tim and Joe, who attend Seattle Pacific University. Jon and Anne are the West Coast Regional Directors for FMBQ.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>I can't remember very many specific quizzes. I know that I had good years and bad years, and was on some successful teams, and some that were less so. I can remember my very first practice. I joined quizzing a few weeks late and my first week of study was on Romans chapter 4. I went home and tried to memorize as many verses as I could. I didn't get the whole chapter, but did get around 15 verses. I quoted them to a coach who seemed very happy! I don't think I ever had a year where I learned the whole material, but I was always a “decent chunk” guy. I can also remember a practice during my Acts year where one teammate was trying to remember the name Blastus and couldn't. So two other guys pretended they were blowing something up with dynamite to try and help jog her memory with “blast-us.” It didn't work.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Evangelical Free Church quizzing did not have individual quizzing, so the only chances for winning came as a team. I can remember taking first place several times at the District level (kind of like FM Regionals), but I'm not sure which years. I can't remember the highest one of my own teams placed at the national level. But I do remember a high school team from Hershey that took second place when I was in middle school. It came down to the last question, and one of our quizzers, who did not know the material as well as two or three others on our team, got too excited about being the hero and jumped way too early. So we got second instead of first.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>I don't know! I can remember lots. How about Acts 4:12-13: “Salvation is found in no one else, for there is no other name under heaven given to mankind by which we must be saved. When they saw the courage of Peter and John and realized that they were unschooled, ordinary men, they were astonished and they took note that these men had been with Jesus.”</answer>
			<answer> I like that they were ordinary and obviously had the ability to do what they did because of the Holy Spirit, and that Jesus was getting the credit.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I was hanging around good friends, going on road trips, having fun. Of course I was getting really familiar with big sections of the Bible. But the biggest effects from quizzing are probably in the answer to the next question.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Well, I have gone on to be a pastor for most of my career, and now a Bible teacher at a Christian High school. So knowing so much Scripture has been a constant benefit in those areas. Of course, I have continued to get even more familiar with it, in part as I've continued to be involved in quizzing as an adult. But classes in college and Seminary were that much easier whenever Bible knowledge was required. My preaching and teaching have benefited from it. Random circumstances will bring Scriptures to mind a lot more frequently than they would have otherwise. Quizzing was a huge part of pointing me and preparing me for the path I have taken.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>My full time job is ministry-oriented. Teaching Bible to middle school and high school students at Moses Lake Christian Academy is a real blessing. But outside of work, my wife and I are both involved in our church. Three friends and myself are the second worship team and get the call whenever the first team can't make it work. I will frequently fill in as the preacher for our Pastor when he will be gone. I get to do that at a handful of other churches in our community as well. I also serve in the Nursery about once a month.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Michelle Boggs" inducted="2019" participated="1981-1985" church="Monacrest Free Methodist Church" city="Monacrest" state="PA" image="m_boggs.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Michelle Boggs is the head quizzing coach and youth director at Ellwood City FM Church in Ellwood City, Pennsylvania. She manages the Big House Youth Center, is married to Gary, and has four daughters (Alaina, Brianna, Larissa, and Sabrina) and one son (Caleb).</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>I enjoyed the competition, but I loved learning the scripture, meeting new people, and traveling; friends become more than friends when you travel in a 15-passenger van from PA to WA. The trip to Seattle was a major highlight for me because I had never been more than a couple states from home, and our team placed 1st in our division that year. As a coach and quizmaster, it has been a joy to see teens grow in their faith and a blessing to watch my own children mature through this ministry.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>In 1983, our team placed 1st in the Senior Teen Novice division at Nationals in Seattle. I don’t know all the stats, but we won several 1st place championships on the conference level and placed at Regionals and Nationals. In Individuals, I placed at Regional and Conference tournaments, and won my division at Conference Finals in 1983 and 1984</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>While quizzing, my favorite verse was “I can do all things through him who gives me strength” (Philippians 4:13).</answer>
			<answer>I didn’t have a lot of confidence as a teen, and this verse helped me realize that Christ was my strength, no matter what the situation. When I was struggling, this was always the first verse that would come to mind.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing showed me that I was valuable, to both God and others. The Scriptures we studied showed me who I was in Christ. The love and mentoring I received from my coach, Evie Smith, and those in the quizzing community, allowed me to become confident in my faith and gave me direction and purpose.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>At the time I quizzed, I was the only Christian in a family of twelve. If I had not quizzed, I may not have stayed in church and would not have met my husband and many other people who have become “family” to me. Quizzing is directly responsible for growing my faith as a teen and putting me on the path to youth ministry. The Scriptures I studied in Bible quizzing have stuck with me and have become my favorites when teaching youth.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am the head coach for Ellwood City and a quizmaster for Pittsburgh (Harvest)/Keystone Conference, regional tournaments, and Nationals.</answer>
			<answer>Besides Bible quizzing, I serve as the youth director at the Ellwood City FM Church and Big House Ministries. I am also a delegate to our annual conference, a member of the worship team, and an LMC.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	
	<inductee name="Phil Lancaster" inducted="2019" participated="1984-1990 " church="Spring Arbor Free Methodist Church" city="Spring Arbor" state="MI" image="p_lancaster.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Phil lives in Spring Arbor, Michigan. His mother, Sherry, was on a championship team in the 1960s.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>In 10th grade at a Chicago tournament, I was the guy off the bench for once (not the star). I got the last question to win the Final.</answer>
			<answer>I was recognized as a champion at a World BQ meet using points per question averages when I was in seventh grade ... this brought my father to tears, recognizing for the first time that I could do this. This would be my "sport."</answer>
			<answer>I finished 8th out of 20 in a World BQ competition where they didn't have a "JV" division, so I was up against high schoolers as a seventh grader.</answer>
			<answer>In 9th or 10th grade, I tied with Peter Samuelson for the sixth spot in Individual Finals.</answer>
			<answer>In 9th grade my team won the World BQ quiz in Chicago.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>John 8:1 "But Jesus went to the Mount of Olives … "</answer>
			<answer>This was the verse with the answer to the last question to win a championship.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It was a place where I (someone in a wheelchair due to cerebral palsy) could compete with my mind on a level playing field with able-bodied peers … and win.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What would you say is the value of Bible Quizzing for other young people?">
			<answer>Growing up as a teenager is hard enough and kids do stupid things. But maybe having some verses in their heads will help them to make a better choice in the moment and avoid some trouble.</answer>
			<answer>But remember … while winning is the goal in FMBQ, it's not the PURPOSE.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Jerry Mullis" inducted="2018" participated="1985-2005" church="Bedford Free Methodist Church" city="Bedford" state="IN" image="j_mullis.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>It was my privilege to coach Bible Quiz Teams from the Bedford Free Methodist Church for 21 years.  During that time I had some of the greatest young people anyone could have wished for.  They were dedicated to the program, each other, learning scripture, and most important, growing in Christ.  Three of those young people were my own daughters and I thank God for a program that enabled my children and their teammates to memorize God’s Word, make lifelong friends, and have fun doing so.  Two of my Bedford quizzers actually met and chose as their life partners a fellow quizzer from another Free Methodist Church.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Working together, I was privileged to coach three Young Teen Rookie National Champions; five Young Teen Veteran National Champions; one Senior Teen Rookie National Champion; and six Senior Teen Veteran Alpha Omega Champions. </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>My favorite scripture is Philippians 4:13 “I can do all things through Christ who gives me strength.”  I gave my heart to Christ as a young boy and now I am getting old, but this scripture has taken me through some very difficult moments in life and I have found that Jesus is the answer every time.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzers always seem to love those overnighters and long trips to a quiz meet.  I wish I could have said the same, but I have wonderful memories of listening to the chatter and songs on a long bus trip. </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>My present involvement in the quiz program is as a stand-in helper and advisor even when the advice is unsolicited.  My number one role today is spectator and cheerleader for my grandchildren who are quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Bible Quizzing, along with mission trips are the best programs the denomination offers our youth.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Karyl Kaufmann" inducted="2018" participated="1960-1964 " church="Youth for Christ" city="Niagara Falls" state="NY" image="k_kaufmann.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Score enough points to qualify for the All-Star team 4 years in a row.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Memorizing verses that I remember and go to even today.  Getting to be on the All Star team and getting to travel to many exciting places like Ocean City, NJ. </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Philippians 4:6-7.  So many times in my life I have gone through tough times and I always go back to the instructions in verse 6 in order to claim verse 7</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It gave me more confidence and made me feel special.  It grounded me in the Word of God.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>The verses I memorized in quizzing are the ones I use so often to help me in my life. </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way?">
			<answer>Last year I finished coaching my last teen after coaching since 1968. </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am working with my husband helping to promote Bible Educational Games to be used in bringing families together around the Word of God.  My husband and I take care of two elderly gentlemen in our home.  We also take in people who need help.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
    <inductee name="Lynette Hose" inducted="2018" participated="2000-2014 " church="Vincennes Free Methodist Church" city="Vincennes" state="IN" image="l_hose.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Lynette Hose worked with the Vincennes, Indiana, quiz teams from 2000-14.</answer>
			<answer>During this time, from 2002-14, she served as the volunteer nurse for the National Bible Quiz Finals. She attended her final nationals in 2015, but was unable to serve as the nurse.</answer>
			<answer>Lynette worked closely with the Vincennes quizzers helping them memorize, listening to them quote, keeping time for practice quizzes and encouraging them to stay motivated and keep doing their best. She started when her sons, David and Jonathan began their quiz careers and even continued after they graduated. She was a great encouragement.</answer>
			<answer>During Lynette’s long hospital and nursing home stays, David, her oldest son, read the entire New Testament to Lynette, but he read Philippians four times, as this was one of her favorite portions of the Bible and she asked him to repeat it.</answer>
			<answer>Lynette was determined to discipline herself into the character of Christ. She most certainly noticed that some of hallmarks of the Apostle Paul’s letter to the servants at Philippi were thanksgiving, joy and encouragement. She demonstrated this same attitude as that of Christ Jesus.</answer>
			<answer>Lynette poured her life into serving Christ in her family, church, nursing, community, country, friends, and Bible Quizzing until her health failed.</answer>
			<answer>Lynette’s family offers their utmost gratitude for this thoughtful and fitting honor and tribute.</answer>
			<answer>As she would repeat and sing often, “Rejoice in the Lord always. I will say it again: Rejoice” Philippians 4:4</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Sheryl Moore" inducted="2018" participated="1973-1979" church=" Free Methodist Church" city="Greenville" state="IL" image="s_moore.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>I loved the comradeship of being on a team.  I enjoyed studying with my team mates and cheering other teams on from our conference when they went further than we did.  I loved the electric atmosphere during the Final Round of the tournament.</answer>
			<answer>Our team got the Spit Shine Award 2 times.  That was when they were actual outfits and not just a T Shirt.</answer>
			<answer>I received a Bible for being on the All-Star Team one year.  I was very excited and proud to be on it. </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1st in 1973 and 1974</answer>
			<answer>2nd in 1977 and 1978</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>I have favorite scriptures from each year I quizzed so it’s difficult to pick just one.  Some favorites offered comfort.  Some were prayers.  Others were beautiful passages about the nature of God.  Others were promises from God.  Still others were instructions for living a Godly life.  Some favorites are below:</answer>
			<answer>Peace I leave with you.  My peace I give you.  I do not give to you as the world gives.  Do not let your hearts be troubled and do not be afraid.  John 14:27</answer>
			<answer>Oh, the depth of the riches of the wisdom and knowledge of God!  How unsearchable his judgments, and his </answer>
			<answer>ths beyond tracing out!  Who has known the mind of the Lord?  Or who has been his counselor?”  “Who has ever given to God, that God should repay them?”  For from him and through him and for him are all things.  To him be the glory forever! Amen.  Romans 11:33-36</answer>
			<answer>I pray that out of his glorious riches he may st</answer>
			<answer>rengthen you with power through his Spirit in your inner being, so that Christ may dwell in your hearts through faith.  And I pray that you, being rooted and established in love, may have power, together with all the Lord’s holy people to grasp how wide and long and high and deep is the love of Christ, and to know this love that surpasses knowledge—that you may be filled to the measure of all the fullness of God.  Ephesians 3:16-19</answer>
			<answer>Praise be to the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of compassion and the God of all comfort, who comforts us in all our troubles, so that we can comfort those in any trouble with the comfort we ourselves receive from God.  2 Corinthians 1:3-4</answer>
			<answer>Consider it pure joy, my brothers and sisters, whenever you face trials of many kinds, because you know that the testing of your faith produces perseverance.  Let perseverance finish its work so that you may be mature and complete, not lacking anything.  James 1:2-4</answer>
			<answer>If any of you lacks wisdom, you should ask God, who gives generously to all without finding fault, and it will be given to you.  James 1:5 </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Since I was studying God’s word, I learned a lot about God’s love for us and his constant presence.  Quizzing helped me be more knowledgeable about God and because of the competition and stress that comes with it, I was able to draw on the promises to help me through it as well as situations that came up outside of quizzing. </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I didn’t memorize everything at the beginning, but the passages I did memorize stuck with me and they come to me at times when I need encouragement, etc.  Because I studied each book or group of book(s) for a year, I can easily find passages when I want to look up something even for the years when I didn’t memorize everything.  The books I did memorize are some of my favorite books in the Bible:  John, Romans, James, Galatians-Colossians.  Because I learned a lot of verses that are helpful for different situations in life, I have been able to give those verses to friends when they needed comfort or encouragement. </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way?">
			<answer>This year I coach a Young Teen Veteran team at WayPoint Free Methodist Church. </answer>
			<answer>When I moved to Clarkson Free Methodist (now WayPoint) after I got married, they didn’t have a quiz team so I asked Pastor Clancy Thompson if I could start one.  He said yes, so I coached it for several years and then helped by being a quizmaster when my kids were little.  When my girls were older they were all in quizzing and I began coaching again and still coach.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I serve on the Finance Team at WayPoint, lead a Care Group with my husband, Glen, and coach a Bible Quiz Team. </answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Charley Canon" inducted="2017" participated="1965-1966 " church="McClellandtown Free Methodist Church" city="McClellandtown" state="PA" image="c_canon.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1st place at Nationals in Young Teen Rookie in 2004 with our son, Charles, and daughter, Lindsay, on the team - coaching</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Psalm 121:1-2 I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills from wence cometh my strength? MY STRENGTH COMETH FROM THE LORD.... (KJV) Although this verse did not come from Bible Quizzing, it has provide a source of understanding and perspective to guide my life.</answer>
			<answer>My first contact with Bible Quizzing goes back to 1958 the year of studying the book of Genesis when I would help my father who was coaching a team at East Liverpool,Ohio - Oakland (Pittsburgh) by trying to jump judge in the days before jump seats.</answer>
			<answer>Any thing that I have accomplished through the Bible Quizzing ministry has been possible due to the support and shared effort of my wife, Linda and this recognition is equally hers.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Created friendships and provided the base for coming back to quizzing as a coach nearly 20 years later</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Hopefully through quizzing I have been able to affect the lives of others by encouragement and through the Word of God. Quizzing has been a vital part of our family life and it is my prayer that it will continue to be through those who have been part of the ministry.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I serve on the Ministerial Appointments Committee and the Ministerial Education and Guidance Board of the Genesis Conference. I teach Free Methodist History at Northeastern Seminary and serve on the Denominational Committee on History and Archives.</answer>
			<answer>Along with my wife, Linda, we assist our daugher Lindsay who is now the coach at Batavia/Northgate (Genesis) and this current year we also assisted Pastor Chris Hoppe-Spink with the team at Buffalo/Cornerstone (Genesis). Chris was on our team at Northgate in 1983.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Ron Lyon" inducted="2017" participated="1984-1989" church="Pearce Memorial Free Methodist Church" city="North Chili" state="NY" image="r_lyon.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>All the trips and the time with friends! Since we were the first team in western NY, we did a lot of traveling in order to compete. I loved the road trips to PA, IN, MI, OH, and of course, Nationals. We had a special couple in our church, Bud and Sandy Conley, who used to drive our team to tournaments in their motor home. It was such a blessing to be together as a team to study and play games.</answer>
			<answer>My first Dairy Queen Blizzard in 1986 when Nationals were at Central College in McPherson, KS!</answer>
			<answer>Being named the Charter Member of the Pearce Memorial Bible Quiz team when I graduated.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Notable Results</answer>
			<answer>1st place STR team in 1985 at the Spring Arbor Regional. They had this multi-day tournament set up for teams as a prep for Nationals, or a year end tournament for those who weren’t going to Nationals. (Nationals were held in August in Estes Park, CO as part of IYC.)</answer>
			<answer>Other highlights:</answer>
			<answer>5th place STV team in 1988 at Nationals at Greenville</answer>
			<answer>7th place STV team in 1989 at Nationals at Seattle Pacific</answer>
			<answer>As a Coach:</answer>
			<answer>1st place YTR team in 2010 at Nationals at Greenville</answer>
			<answer>1st place YTR team in 2013 at Nationals at Roberts Wesleyan</answer>
			<answer>Alpha and Omega team in 2016 at Nationals at Seattle Pacific</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Hebrews 12:1-2 The encouragement and motivation it provides</answer>
			<answer>Matthew 11:28-30 The comfort and hope it provides</answer>
			<answer>Hebrews 4:12</answer>
			<answer>I Corinthians 10:13</answer>
			<answer>I Corinthians 10:31</answer>
			<answer>Hebrews 13:5-6</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I learned more of God’s Word than I would have had I not been in quizzing. Studying it and memorizing it affected the choices I made and the way I lived, because I had God’s Word directing me and guiding me. The guidance and support I received from my coaches, as well as their examples of Christian living, really influenced my life as well. Finally, the friendships I developed with my teammates really strengthened my faith. We talked together, prayed together, and encouraged and supported each other as Christians.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>The continued impact quizzing has had is amazing! I still know quotes I memorized, and they provide comfort, guidance, encouragement, wisdom, and strength when needed. Many verses and passages have become more meaningful as I experience life as a husband and parent, than they were when I was a teen. God’s Word is living and active, and always relevant! I’m so thankful that all 4 of my kids have quizzed or are current quizzers.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am currently the head coach at Freechurch. Freechurch was a church plant that started in 2010, and I started the quiz team in 2012. Prior to Freechurch, I was a coach at New Hope (Rochester, NY), Park Ridge (Rochester, NY), and Pearce Memorial (Rochester, NY)</answer>
			<answer>In addition to Bible Quizzing, I am currently the team lead for our Usher team at church, and help with the Finance team. I was part of the launch team that started Freechurch, have been on the church board, and was a delegate to the conference. Over the past 2 decades, I have also served as a Sunday school teacher in Kids JAM, a leader in Boys Brigade, and a coach for Upward Basketball and Happy 5 Soccer.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Dan Bartholomew" inducted="2016" participated="na" church="Rainier Avenue Free Methodist Church" city="Seattle" state="WA" image="d_bartholomew.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>This is probably the highest honor I could receive in this life, and I think that is probably because Bible Quizzing has meant so much to me, and will continue to do so.  We have 7 children and 5 of them quizzed for 9 years, one for 7 and half years and one for 5 years. But really, the most impact has been on my own life and hopefully in the lives of the kids that have been involved.  Our immediate family has 87 years of Bible Quizzing logged. I have kept a log since the first year I began and have had over 200 kids on Bible Quiz teams with over 400 years total of Bible Quizzing participation. But what really matters is that if only one person is in heaven because of my involvement in this ministry, my life is one that made a difference to God. My only aim is to finish the race and complete the task the Lord Jesus has given me, the task of loving kids and introducing them to the good news of God's grace.</answer>
			<answer>I was raised in the Christian and Missionary Alliance church and we were not involved in Bible Quizzing there. I did see a demonstration once. I became involved because my oldest son wanted to do quizzing when he entered fourth grade (as we have Junior Quizzing).</answer>
			<answer>Within six months, I was coaching his team and continued in that role until I became co-director of the PNW conference for 3 years and directed by myself for 3 more years. But my heart has always been with coaching, so after stepping down as director, I have continued coaching ever since. I have been the church director at Rainier Avenue Church for about 10 years now and we have now had over 100 quizzers here.  At our most, we had 31 quizzers on 10-11 teams, and right now we have 13 quizzers with many more young people approaching quizzing age.</answer>
			<answer>I started out at Eastside Free Methodist in Bellevue and when they disbanded, we attended Timberlake Christian Fellowship (FM) in Redmond for 3 years.  A new church plant had been started in our home town, so, for the next 10 years, I coached at Mountain Creek Christian Fellowship (FM) in Issaquah.  Since our kids graduated from high school, we have attended Rainier Avenue FM church in Seattle for ten years as they are a multi-ethnic congregation much like our own family.  We have 2 biological children and adopted twins from Korea as well as adopted triplets from Haiti. We adopted the triplets after going on two medical missionary trips there.</answer>
			<answer>Many of the highlights of my coaching career stem from kids with challenges.  One year I had a team of three kids, of which none could read very well. My first team had a girl who had quizzed for 2 and a half years and had not answered one question, but the last half of the year she answered 4 questions and received the most improved quizzer award.  I have had ADDHD kids and kids from broken families. They provide the much inspiration for me when you see that light that comes in their eyes while Bible Quizzing.  One boy I had did not answer one question all year but at regional finals when playing for the championship, he answered the 14th question to help us send the match into overtime. My biggest joy is showing families that we love their kids.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>We took the YTR championship at Roberts in 2007, defeating Wilmore in Super Finals.  My daughter, Elizabeth won the Dave Markell  award in 2000. Other highlights were when Rainier Avenue took 2nd place in the STV team division at SPU in 2012 and when I coached our YTV team and they took 2nd place at Spring Arbor in 2000.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>My favorite scripture is James 1:22 "Do not merely listen to the word and so deceive yourselves. Do what it says." We were in a Bible study for 9 years when I came to realize that I could study for the rest of my life, but unless I actually got out there and did what the Bible said to do, I was deceiving myself.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am still the Rainier Avenue church Bible Quiz director and coach of one of the teams. My wife and I are also in the nursery and coordinate it for Sunday mornings.  You can't start recruiting for Bible Quizzing too soon.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Dave Clark" inducted="2016" participated="1991-2008" church="Auburn Free Methodist Church" city="Auburn" state="WA" image="d_clark.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1996 - Senior Teen Veteran ‘B’ - coaching</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Philippians 4:13 - “I can do everything through Christ who gives me strength.” We won our first Senior Teen Veteran Regional Finals championship on that quote and it reminds me that God equips us for everything he calls us to do.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It has grounded my family in God’s word, given us an extended ‘family’ to fellowship with and strengthened my love for God and His word.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>PNW Conference Director for Bible quizzing and I serve as a worship leader in my church.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Betty Clark" inducted="2016" participated="1991-2008" church="Auburn Free Methodist Church" city="Auburn" state="WA" image="b_clark.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1968 - STV - 3rd place</answer>
			<answer>1996 - Senior Teen Veteran ‘B’ - coaching</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Hebrews 11:1 - “Now faith is being sure of what we hope for and certain of what we do not see.” My faith in God, expressed in this verse, has helped me through some difficult times.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It gave our family a framework for studying the Bible together.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I serve in Bible Quizzing on the statistics team and am a vocalist on the worship team in our church.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Glenn and Louise Hasslinger" inducted="2016" participated="1982-2015" church="Timberlake Free Methodist Church" city="Redmond" state="WA" image="gl_hasslinger.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>The joy of seeing teens getting close to the Lord and growing in their faith.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>4th in 84 and 7th place in 2012. However we were all winners because of getting God’s word in us and lives changed by the power of the scriptures.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Many! But to pick one… 2 Timothy 3:16,17 “All Scripture is God-breathed and is useful for teaching, rebuking, correcting and training in righteousness, so that the man of God may be thoroughly equipped for every good work.” Why? Because this explains the main reason for being involved in FM Bible Quizzing. (My favorite book is James followed by John.)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="For how long and where were you active in quizzing?">
			<answer>We were involved in Quizzing 1982 through 1999 and 2003 through 2015, 29 years over a 33 year span.  We started at Eastside FM in Bellevue, WA (as coaches) which then merged into Timberlake in Redmond, WA. I started Quiz-mastering about 1985.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It has made me a better person. It has forced me to study deeper in the scriptures which has given me a wonderful insight to God’s purpose for our lives.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Roger Stone" inducted="2016" participated="1986-1990" church="Lawrence Free Methodist Church" city="Lawrence" state="KS" image="r_stone.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Making individual finals as YTR (1987) and as STV (1989, 1990). </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>STV runner-up in 1989 at Seattle.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Acts 20:24. This verse sums up what was Paul’s philosophy of life. I want the same for my life.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It gave me the incentive to study the Scriptures seriously on my own and gave me a hunger to know God and His Word.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I am sure Bible quizzing is the main reason that I have ended up as a Bible translator. My passion for the Word of God was kindled as a young man memorizing chapters for quizzing. My desire to help others grow in their faith was developed while serving as a coach while in college. My analytical skills in analyzing meaning versus form were developed as a quizmaster.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing?">
			<answer>I am helping coordinate Free Methodist Bible quizzing in the Philippines and also starting a different form of Bible quizzing for the Ayta Mag-Indi people of the Philippines.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I serve with Wycliffe Bible Translators as a Bible Translation Consultant. I am also Translation Coordinator for the Ayta cluster where I have active involvement in working with two committees (Ayta Mag-Indi and Ayta Abellen) of Mother tongue translators who are translating the New Testament and other Scripture materials into their own languages.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="John Anderson" inducted="2015" participated="1983-1988" church="Columbus First Free Methodist Church" city="Columbus" state="IN" image="j_anderson.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>When I was a pre-teen, growing up in Columbus, Indiana, I had dreams of playing basketball or driving a race car in the INDY 500. Of course, growing to the full height of 5’10” and coming from a family that did not the exorbitant amount of money it takes to race in the INDY 500, my child-hood ambitions were not meant to be.</answer>
			<answer>I was not raised in a religious family and specifically not a Christian family. I began attending the Free Methodist Church because I wanted to get to know a young lady who was a member of the Free Methodist Church. Eventually, I was introduced to Bible Quizzing and the competitiveness of Quizzing intrigued me.</answer>
			<answer>The Columbus, Indiana Free Methodist Church is located at the corner of Maple Avenue and 22nd Street. In 1969 I started attending the church and before long I was asked to join the Church league basketball team; I also played the lead role in the Christmas play and participated in other FMY activities. But it would not be until 1983 that I would accept Christ as my personal Saviour.</answer>
			<answer>In early 1970, I was invited to the FMY Bible Quiz practice and I thought it was interesting. It was competitive, it was physical with the jumping aspect, and I thought it would be an opportunity to meet girls and have fun. I was a casual participant on the 1969/70 team when we Quizzed on 1st and 2nd Corinthians.</answer>
			<answer>In 1970/71, I became more focused on the techniques of Bible Quiz study, rules and competition.   It was during the process of learning to memorize segments of Matthew that I discovered a technique that helped me to overcome my dyslexia. I also discovered that Bible Quizzing could provide peer-approval and acceptance which was not a part of my home-life. My parents marriage full of turmoil, alcoholism and unfaithfulness; I was often left on my own and rarely received approval or encouragement.</answer>
			<answer>In 1971/72 the Columbus Free Methodist Bible Quiz team competed in every tournament within the Wabash Conference and a few nearby conferences, too. In all of the tournaments we competed in during that year we lost a total of 3 quizzes (2 quizzes during the season and 1 quiz at the finals and no team beat us twice). I was the team Captain.</answer>
			<answer>As I participated in Bible Quizzing, I was impressed with the compassionate Christian attitude of Quizzers and their Coaches. The Kaufmann Family Quizzers of Greenville, Coach Stan Hoke of West Morris Street and many others made such an impression on me that in spite of my personal un-Christ-like Quizzing persona, I could not help but to be moved by their compassion and gentle spirits. I was, in many ways, envious of what (or rather Who) they had and I did not.</answer>
			<answer>Early in the 1971/72 Bible Quiz year, I set as our team goal to win the Championship. So we dedicated ourselves to do anything it would take to win. As Captain, I was the rules expert and memorized both books. Our number one quizzer memorized both books and could start in the middle and quote a verse in alternating directions without missing a word. However, since no one on the team was a Christian, our behavior, morals, and ethics became inappropriate and caused three coaches to abandon the team.</answer>
			<answer>While Quizzing I was perplexed by Paul’s writings, especially Romans chapter 7. When Paul went into detail about ‘what he wanted to do but could not do and therefore did the things that he did not want to do’; I believe that Paul was a hypocrite. Later I would understand that without the presence of Christ in my life and the tutor-ship of the Holy Spirit I could not comprehend the meaning of God’s Word.</answer>
			<answer>In 1972 at the University of Illinois, we won the International Championship of Bible Quizzing. But it was a hallow victory. Without Christ, it was only a plaque, a prize Bible and a $1,000 scholarship that would never be used.</answer>
			<answer>Although I became very successful in business my personal life began falling apart. In the mid-1977 I became a cocaine addict. In October of 1982 I lost everything and was homeless. But while homeless in San Diego, California, I went to a Rescue Mission where Romans 6:23 was boldly painted on the side of their building. I was former Championship Quizzer who had memorized Romans and Galatians; I knew Romans 6:23… For the wages of sin is death, but the free gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.</answer>
			<answer>When I saw Romans 6:23, I thought that God was mocking me for the mess I had made of my life. After all, I was a very successful young business man who had anything he wanted but threw it all away; I had a failed marriage; I was a drug addict; I was a failure; and now I was homeless. God had to be mocking me by having Romans 6:23 painted on the side of a Rescue Mission for me!</answer>
			<answer>For three months I lived as a homeless man on the street in San Diego.   Every day I would go to the Rescue Mission for a free meal or to use their showers or to receive clean clothes and every day I would read Romans 6:23. Finally, I came to realize what was missing in my life; it was the saving knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ. On January 17, 1983 at 1:25PM I fell to my knees in the old San Diego Rescue Mission and accepted Jesus Christ as my Saviour.</answer>
			<answer>The verse of scripture I hated (Romans 6:23) I now loved. That verse and Bible Quizzing were used by God to rescue me!</answer>
			<answer>During the final months of 1982 and into 1983, I can attest to the fact that our Lord and Saviour literally used Bible Quizzing to Rescue me! Because I had memorized Romans and Galatians and understood the meaning of “The wages of sin is death, but the free gift of God is eternal life through Christ Jesus our Lord”, God used those words to prick my heart and bring me to the realization that it was Christ and Christ alone who would and could rescue me from this body of death.</answer>
			<answer>God delivered me from my addiction to cocaine. He gave me a new heart. He gave me a love for Him and the scriptures and an infinity and love for the lost, especially the homeless and impoverished who are at a high risk of perishing without our Saviour. Bible Quizzing made and continues to make a difference in my life, even today.</answer>
			<answer>After accepting Jesus as my Saviour on January 17, 1983, I joined the San Diego Rescue Mission’s discipleship program which provides recovery from homelessness in a Christ-centered atmosphere. Later that year, after much prayer and guidance, I was asked by the Rescue Mission’s Executive Director to join the Rescue Mission’s staff. During the next eight years I did everything there is to do at a rescue mission, serving as the Assistant Director from 1989 through 1990.</answer>
			<answer>In January of 1991, when the Executive Director retired, I was asked by the Board of Directors to serve as interim Executive Director; which I did until August of 1993. In August of 1993, I was called to the Bay Area Rescue Mission where I was ordained in 1994. On January 1, 2000, I became the President/CEO of the Bay Area Rescue Mission which is located in Richmond, California, across the Bay from San Francisco.</answer>
			<answer>I am a member of Valley Bible Church in Hercules, California and serve on their Radio program advisory Board. I’ve served as President of the Association of Gospel Rescue Missions Pacific District and assisted with the founding of two additional Rescue Missions. I’ve also served on several other Boards over the years.</answer>
			<answer>In 2015, I contacted Free Methodist Bible Quiz with the idea of implementing Bible Quiz Bible Study at the Bay Area Rescue Mission. I believed the Lord was leading us to establish a Bible Quiz program, modeled after FMY Bible Quizzing, for the formerly homeless men and women in our Discipleship programs.</answer>
			<answer>In May, 2015, I purchased and donated 2 sets of jump chairs to the Bay Area Rescue Mission. In June we began a summer introductory Bible Quiz Bible Study program and launched it by Quizzing on Romans Chapter 8. When the next FMY Bible Quiz year starts in September of 2015, the Bay Area Rescue Mission will begin a Bible Quiz Bible Study course which will coincide with the Free Methodist program and we will study the book of The Acts of the Apostles.</answer>
			<answer>As of July, 12, 2015, the Bay Area Rescue Mission has 60 formerly homeless men and 30 formerly homeless women in our Bible Quiz program. If God permits (and the Free Methodist Bible Quiz Program allows), we hope to bring a men’s team and a women’s team to participate in QUIC Quizzing in 2016 Bible Quiz Finals in Seattle, Washington.</answer>
			<answer>It is truly an amazing honor to be included in the Free Methodist Bible Quiz Hall of Fame. Yes, God used Bible Quizzing and Rescue Mission Ministry to touch my heart and save and rescue me.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Tanner Bouchie" inducted="2014" participated="2002-2009 " church="Vincennes Free Methodist Church" city="Vincennes" state="IN" image="t_bouchie.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Without a doubt, my favorite and most memorable competitive moments were the final rounds in 2008 and 2009 for the privilege to take home the Alpha Omega trophy. Both years, Vincennes quizzed against a very strong team from Marion, Iowa. Both years also required superfinal rounds to determine the champion.</answer>
			<answer>In the superfinal round of 2008, Marion led Vincennes by a score of 140 to 120 going into question number 14, meaning Vincennes needed to earn the points for both of the remaining questions to win. I pre-jumped on question number 14 and completed the question in a very complicated way, making my completion a cross-book question. The quizmaster took several minutes considering my completion, which seemed like hours to me. Eventually, I was allowed to answer my question, and I used every bit of my 20 seconds to answer my question successfully. With the score tied, Vincennes correctly answered the final question, winning the superfinal round.</answer>
			<answer>In 2009, Vincennes and Marion met again in the final rounds, and Marion beat Vincennes by a large margin in the first matchup. In superfinals, a very close quiz ended with Vincennes ahead, which resulted in a second championship.</answer>
			<answer>Another memorable day was the double-elimination tournament at denominational quiz finals in 2007. On that day, the Vincennes Senior Team Veteran team quizzed a total of eight tournament rounds, including six consecutive elimination rounds, ultimately finishing the tournament in 2nd place behind an impressive team from Indianapolis Aldersgate</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>2006 - 1st in Young Teen Veteran team competition </answer>
			<answer>2006 - 1st in Young Teen Veteran individual competition</answer>
			<answer>2007 - 2nd in Senior Teen Veteran team competition</answer>
			<answer>2008 - 1st in Senior Teen Veteran team competition </answer>
			<answer>2008 - 2nd in Senior Teen Veteran individual competition</answer>
			<answer>2009 - 1st in Senior Teen Veteran team competition</answer>
			<answer>2009 - 1st in Senior Teen Veteran individual competition</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"You see, at just the right time, while we were still powerless, Christ died for the ungodly. Very rarely will anyone die for a righteous man, though for a good man someone might possibly dare to die. But God demonstrates his own love for us in this: While we were still sinners, Christ died for us." Romans 5:6-8</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing allowed me a healthy, intellectual, and spiritually-fulfilling way to exercise my competitive spirit. Not only did was the memorization of scripture itself a blessing, but quizzing connected me to a large number of people who positively impacted me as well.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>The systematic memorization of God's Word has created foundation on which the rest of my life sets. Knowing both the content and context of books of the Bible has allowed me to stand strong in my faith, and it has also challenged me to continuously dig deeper into scripture and examine my faith.</answer>
			<answer>For the word of God is living and active. Sharper than any double-edged sword, it penetrates, even to dividing soul and spirit, joints and marrow; it judges the thoughts and attitudes of the heart." Hebrews 4:12</answer>
			<answer>Furthermore, through quizzing, I have met many people whom I consider lifelong friends. Fellow quizzers, coaches, quizmasters, and even some quizzing spectators have impacted my life. This ministry was a blessing to me when I was a teenager, and it has continued to bless me today.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I quizmaster frequently at quiz meets in Indiana. I have occasionally served as a quizmaster at denominational quiz finals.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>While in law school, I have been actively involved with the Christian Legal Society, working to build up my fellow brothers and sisters in Christ. At my church, I serve in ministries wherever there is opportunity, most recently assisting with a Vacation Bible School.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="David Hose" inducted="2012" participated="2000-2003" church="Vincennes Free Methodist Church" city="Vincennes" state="IN" image="d_hose.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>2001 - National Individual Runner-Up (McPherson, KS)</answer>
			<answer>2002 - The Vincennes Tall vs. Vincennes Short final round</answer>
			<answer>2002 - National Team Champions (Seattle, WA)</answer>
			<answer>2003 - National Individual 4th Place (Rochester, NY)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>It is hard to lay my finger on one specific scripture, but I would have to say that I Corinthians 13 would be the one I would have to choose. The year we quizzed over I and II Corinthians was exciting and overwhelming. With the teammates I had, every practice was almost like a national finals. I Corinthians 13 became a personal challenge, and I succeeded in quoting the entire chapter within the 20 second limit in a quiz. However, the picture of God, painted within the words of this chapter, has brought me to a better understanding of what love is, and, more importantly, who God is, because God is love.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>The quizzing ministry forced me to ask questions that I would not have known to ask had I not been so focused on the word of God. It brought me lifelong friendships as well as a heart for studying the scriptures and helping impact young people for Christ.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>In a round about way, quizzing led me to my choice of college, as I decided to attend Oakland City University with David Swank, my teammate. I met my wife while in college, so I owe the Bible quizzing program a great deal.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I currently help out at quizzes when I can. I have made it to nationals every year since I started, including planning our wedding and honeymoon around the national tournament in 2008. This will be my ninth year as a quizmaster, which, counting my three years as a quizzer, marks my twelfth year being involved with this powerful ministry.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am currently working in the athletic department at Oakland City University, a Christian school in southern Indiana. My wife and I are also the dorm directors for the underclassmen girls' dorm on campus. We are active with our local church family as well as in many ministry outlets on campus.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="David Swank" inducted="2012" participated="1996-2002" church="Vincennes Free Methodist Church" city="Vincennes" state="IN" image="d_swank.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>I really enjoyed Nationals every year, it was a great experience to not only compete, but to have a good time with other quizzers from your own team and other teams that you didn't get to see as often.</answer>
			<answer>The no-missed prejumps rule our team had my senior year. If you missed a prejump you had to sub out. We had Adam King, Rachel (Coates) Truitt, David Hose and myself and we all had it memorized pretty well so it gave everyone a chance to get in and to not get too crazy jumping against each other instead of the other team! It also gave the scorekeeper headaches keeping track of all the substitutions.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1997 - YTR A Team 2nd Rochester, NY</answer>
			<answer>1998 - YTV Individuals 6th Spring Arbor, MI</answer>
			<answer>1999 - YTV Individuals 6th YTR "A" Team 1st Greenville, IL</answer>
			<answer>2001 - STV A Team 5th STV Individuals 6th McPherson, KS</answer>
			<answer>2002 - STV A Team 1st Seattle, WA Alpha-Omega Champions</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>After quizzing over so much of the New Testament it is hard to pick just one scripture. I really enjoyed quizzing over the Book of Acts and the early church. </answer>
			<answer>One of my favorites is John 6:66-69 "From this time on many of his disciples turned back and no longer followed him. "You do not want to leave too, do you?" Jesus asked the Twelve. Simon Peter answered him, "LORD, TO WHOM SHALL WE GO? YOU HAVE THE WORDS OF ETERNAL LIFE. We believe and know that you are the Holy One of God." These verses are just so powerful, because Jesus is the only one to turn to no matter what the world throws at you or how hard things may be.</answer>
			<answer>I also like 1st Corinthians 15:33 "Do not be misled: "Bad company corrupts good character"". Without this verse my senior year I don't know how things may have been different after high school. It really shaped who I made a decision to have as friends in my life and I think God used it to keep me following His path.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing gave me another good outlet to my competitive nature. I ran in high school and that strengthened me physically, but quizzing strengthened me spiritually. Just like training to run, it helped build me up with the Word daily and lay a foundation for the future.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Spiritually Bible Quizzing has given me an increased appreciation for the Scripture and a solid foundation of memory verses. Almost anytime the Sunday sermon is from a part of Scripture I studied I can still quote along with a good deal of the passage when it is read! </answer>
			<answer>Also to this day my closest friends are from Bible Quizzing. And almost anywhere I go I find people who I know through Bible Quizzing. When I moved to Indianapolis, two people I only knew through quizzing, Brad and Heather Anderson opened their home and let me stay with them for five months!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>Since I graduated high school I have been to the last ten nationals as a quizmaster and helped out in many of the monthly quizzes during that time.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Presently in addition to helping with Bible Quizzing I am serving the Lord as a student in college living a God centered life and striving to be an example for others.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Bob and Katherine Swank" inducted="2011" participated="none" church="Vincennes Free Methodist Church" city="Vincennes" state="IN" image="bk_swank.jpg">
		<qa question="Where and for what church did you quiz?">
			<answer>I have done Quic quizzing with Vincennes the last several years, but did not quiz as a youth.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Our first Alpha-Omega team in Seattle in 2002 was, in our biased opinion, the best team that we have ever seen. The real highlight, though, is that 3 of the 4 members of that team are still very involved in the quizzing ministry. The fact that so many of our quizzers have continued to be involved in the Bible Quizzing ministry tells us that quizzing did have an impact in their lives. For example, this year at nationals, seven former Vincennes quizzers are here as quizmasters. Watching these quizzers continue to grow is a highlight.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>I have won several individual championships in Quic quizzing.</answer>
			<answer>Vincennes teams that we have coached have won at least one national title in every division, including 3 Alpha-Omega's. (2002, 2008, and 2009)</answer>
			<answer>Vincennes individuals that we have coached have won at least one national title in every division, including 2 in STV.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Do not work for food that spoils, but for food that endures to eternal life, which the Son of Man will give you. On him God the Father has placed his seal of approval." - John 6:27</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I did not quiz as a youth. I attended a church that did not have a quizzing ministry. Even if they would have had quizzing, I probably would not have quizzed as I had other interests in high school and did not become a Christian until I was in college.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Quizzing ministry has inspired me to study the scripture to a much greater extent. Each year I memorize all the material with the quizzers and do an in depth Bible study of that year's material.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I coach the Vincennes team and have been the Director of Quizmasters for the Wabash/New South Conferences the last few years. This year I am also directing the quizmasters at Nationals. I have also just recently assumed duties in updating the National Quiz Rankings.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I have taught an Adult Sunday School class for 35 years. I am also the Chairman of the Vincennes FM Church Finance Committee and a Member of the Vincennes FM Board of Administration.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Evie Smith" inducted="2011" participated="1956-1959" church="Monacrest Free Methodist Church" city="Monacrest" state="PA" image="e_smith.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Competing at Roberts and Camp Mack. But, I had more highlights as a coach.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>I won Pittsburgh Conference and my teams have won divisional championships at Nationals. I had a 1st Individual Senior Teen Veteran champ at IYC in Estes Park.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"And we know that in all things God works for the good of those who love him, who have been called according to his purpose." - Romans 8:28</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I was the only Christian in my family, and quizzing help me learn the Word and showed me love and Christian conduct.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It has kept me in the Word and gave me opportunity to share the Word with many teens ---- even some from other churches-- also in China.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>Yes, still coaching for over 45 years.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>In addition to Bible quizzing --I'm a steward at Monacrest - group leader for Friends of friends, ladies group (interdenominational).</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Bob and Kelly Mueller" inducted="2010" participated="none" church="Emmanuel Free Methodist Church" city="Alton" state="IL" image="bk_mueller.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>We quizzed in QUIC and served as coaches between 1997 and 2008. Bob also served as a quiz box repair technician and seat builder for many of those years.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Bob and I love memorizing Scripture together and thoroughly enjoyed QUIC quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>We placed in the top three a few years for QUIC team and Individuals.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>The highlight for both of us includes all the passages that we carry in our head and in our heart and can still quote today.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>As of April, we both retired from the quizzing ministry, after serving for 13 years (1997-2010).</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>We are mentoring and sponsoring fellowship events for the Young Adults in our church.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Bryan Blankenship" inducted="2010" participated="1979-1985" church="McPherson Free Methodist Church" city="McPherson" state="KS" image="b_blankenship.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Flying to Seattle, WA (my first ever commercial airplane flight) for Quiz Nationals at SPU (1983); quizzing for the Alpha Omega trophy in Estes Park, CO at IYC in front of several thousand peers (1985); and, beating Mary Helen (Brown) Gensch, Tim Huff and a very strong field of STV quizzers in individual finals at a regional quiz meet in Kansas City.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1985 - Alpha Omega Winner</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>My favorite scripture is the entire Gospel of John. This was what we studied my senior year, and I can still quote major sections of it today. And because of this, the Lord is able to bring them to mind time after time when I need to hear a word from HIm. I particularly feed on chapters 13-14 where he spent that amazing evening with His disciples in the upper room, modeling servant leadership for them, as well as on His most intimate teaching and prayer for His disciples in chapters 15-17. (The fact that we will be studying this again in 2010-11 during my own son's senior year makes it even more meaningful to me in these days.)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It kept me in the Word during times where I was finding my own way as a believer and a young man. I was a preacher's kid and had an amazing example set for me by my parents, but like every single one of us, I had to come to a place where I established my own faith apart from my parents, family, youth group, etc. It also gave me an outlet for some of my more competitive drives. Having had the curse of being a pretty decent athlete but growing up in a town and a high school that was full of exceptional athletes, when I was unable to make the high school basketball team as a sophomore I was able to continue to turn to quizzing for more than just its spiritual rewards.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>A whole, whole lot! It planted in me the early seeds of a genuine love for God's Word and a continuing desire to memorize it and hide it in my heart as an adult -- not for competitive reasons any longer but for spiritual nourishment and guidance.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>Yes. At the present time I am finishing my fifth year as the coach of the Wilmore, KY Bible quizzing ministry, having re-started it for the church in 2005. This is actually my second stint coaching at Wilmore in a re-start situation. Shortly after arriving in Wilmore to attend Asbury Theological Seminary in 1990, I re-started the ministry for the church and led it for a couple of years. Not to sound like a broken record, but my third coaching stint was in McPherson, KS, where I re-started their dormant program in 2001 and led it for two years before moving back to Wilmore during what would have been my third year of coaching. (Having no idea at the time I would be moving mid-year, I had asked for a one-year "sabbatical" in 2003-2004 before what I thought would begin my son's quizzing time in the fall of 2004 and likely many more years of coaching.)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>In addition to currently coaching Bible quizzing, I just completed four years of assistant coaching for my son's Christian homeschool high school varsity basketball team. I also serve as an assistant teacher in my wife's and my Sunday School class as well as various other roles within our local FMC such as serving as a Delegate, serving on a building committee, and serving currently as chair of the church's nominating committee. I also strongly view my vocational calling and role in the area of finance at Asbury Theological Seminary as a major part of my service to the Lord.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Greg Gossell" inducted="2010" participated="1975-1977" church="Toddville Free Methodist Church" city="Toddville" state="IA" image="g_gossell.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>The experience of Nationals in 1977 was my highlight as a quizzer. I learned in 1977 what it took to be a top quizzer. As a coach and director, I attended every nationals from 1984 to 1999 and they were all highlights.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>I coached from 1983-1996. We won four Alpha-Omegas, and took 2nd four times.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Do you not know that in a race all the runners run, but only one gets the prize? Run in such a way as to get the prize." - 1 Corinthians 9:24 </answer>
			<answer>I believe that God wants us to live our life, and to quiz each quiz, in such a way as to win the prize.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I was only able to quiz two years, and I was very disappointed when my church could not put together a team my last two years of high school.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I believe the disappointment of not being able to fully quiz as a teenager has been a driving force in me to be involved as a adult in quizzing over the last 27 years. I want to give as many teenagers as possible a chance to quiz.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I am currently the director of Summit Bible Quizzing, which is a part of Bible Quiz Fellowship. SBQ is located in Kansas City, and we have 120 youth in our quiz program. While this style of quizzing is different than FM quizzing, the goals and purpose of the ministry is the same, to help young people learn the Word.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Summit Bible Quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Deborah Somerville" inducted="2009" participated="1967-1968" church="Mt. Carmel Free Methodist Church" city="Mt. Carmel" state="IL" image="d_somerville.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Getting to travel and meet kids from other conferences; my church was quite small and we were trying to get a program going. We were not one of the more serious contenders from month to month, but we tried!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Then Peter began to speak: 'I now realize how true it is that God does not show favoritism  but accepts from every nation the one who fears him and does what is right.' " -Acts 10:34-35.</answer>
			<answer>This was perhaps Peter's most profound "A-ha!" moment, as he came to realize through vision and anointing that all people everywhere were candidates for God's grace and the Holy Spirit's indwelling. It was another progression in his ministry and his journey of faith.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It drew me into the Word of God more than I might have been otherwise. It also gave me a greater appreciation and respect for my peers as well as the adults who devoted so much time to the program.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It deepened my knowledge of the Scriptures as a high school student, and that served me well in the years to come. As an adult and quiz coach I celebrated the fact that our son chose to participate, and valued the time he spent in the Word. Even though our daughter was too young at the time, she was impacted positively by spending time with the quizzers.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>At present, my involvement in Bible quizzing is as a support to my local team as the senior pastor of the McPherson (KS) FMC. For several years in the mid-1980s and early 1990s I was a coach at Pearce Memorial Church. When we began the program, there were no teams in that part of the State. The closest were in the Pittsburg Conference. We began building a team and promoting quizzing to other area (Genesee Conference) churches through quiz demonstrations and testimonials from our quizzers. Gradually, the program took hold and grew significantly through the years. It was extremely gratifying to serve as an encourager and coach during that period of time.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I was ordained elder in the Free Methodist Church in June of 2003 in the Gateway Conference, where I served on staff at the Greenville (IL) FMC. In July of 2008 I began my appointment as senior pastor of the McPherson (KS) FMC where I continue to serve.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Nick Willis" inducted="2009" participated="1991-1996" church="Willamina Free Methodist Church" city="Willamina" state="OR" image="n_willis.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>I always loved going to Nationals each year. I loved the competition, the travel, and the people that I would meet.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>My team won the Alpha-Omega trophey in 1992 (James and Jeremy Kramer) and in 1996 (Dan and Patrick Willis and Allan Goodwin). We took second place in 1993 and third place in 1994 and 1995. Teams I have coached have been regional champions for the last two years (Esther Hunt, Hannah Brekke, and Nathan McReynolds)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>My favorite verse is from Galations 2:20. "I have been crucified with Christ and I no longer live but Christ lives in me. The life I live in the body I live by faith in the Son of God who loved me and gave himself for me."</answer>
			<answer>This verse is a constant reminder to me that this life I am living is not about me. It is about Jesus. Jesus gave his life for me, and it is my life goal to use the freedom that he gave me to serve him well.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I went through some tough times as a young Christian teenager. I had friends on drugs, friends that were thinking about suicide, friends who were developing problems with drinking and I was just trying to survive as a young Christian. The word of God was "an anchor for my soul." Quizzing kept me in God's Holy Word every single week and put my feet firmly on the right path. There is nothing as powerful as the words of Jesus to change a young person’s life. I am a testimony to this truth.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>The Word of God is in my heart. I have heard it said before that Bible Quizzing only gives young people head knowledge of the Word and not heart knowledge. These people have very little faith in what the word of God is capable of. If you take in the Word of God on a consistent basis, it WILL find a way of working on your heart. Paul described the Word of God as our Sword in the battle of life. You do not want to go into battle without your sword.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I have stayed involved as a coach and a quizmaster. I started the Bible quiz ministry at Timberview Christian Fellowship in Spokane, Washington and helped to start the Bible quiz program at Opportunity Free Methodist Church in Spokane, Washington.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>For the last four years I have been teaching as a Math Professor at a Christian University in Spokane Washington. Next year I will be teaching at another Christian University (George Fox University) in Newberg, Oregon. I am involved in Worship as a bass player. I also have lead a small group for young married couples for the last two years. I have headed up the Bible Quizzing ministry at Timberview Christian Fellowship for the last two years.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Joel Miller" inducted="2008" participated="1985-1989" church="Bedford Free Methodist Church" city="Bedford" state="IN" image="j_miller.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>The teammates with whom I quizzed became lifelong friends, and those are what I appreciate the most now. Another highlight was the opportunity to travel around the country to the quizzes. My coach, Mark Colgan, also made each week's practice a highlight - we spent hours memorizing the Scripture, but also playing basketball, having fun, and deepening our relationship with each other.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>We won several Wabash Conference championships in different divisions. I won the Wabash Conference ST Individuals in 1987. I placed second in STV Individuals at the 1989 Nationals in Seattle. (My good friends Hans Huffman and Rick Murphy were 1st and 3rd that year.)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>“Do not store up for yourselves treasures on earth, where moths and vermin destroy, and where thieves break in and steal. But store up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where moths and vermin do not destroy, and where thieves do not break in and steal. For where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.</answer>
			<answer>Matthew 6:19-21 continues to be a challenge to me. As a physician, we are programmed from very early on in our training that we deserve the financial rewards that might come our way and we should begin to "store up" that earthly treasure as soon as possible. Even as a missionary, I am tempted to focus on earthly treasures, but these words of Jesus help me re-arrange my priorities and be willing to sacrifice what the world offers for that "treasure in heaven, where moth and rust do not destroy and where thieves do not break in and steal." Jesus' call to self-sacrificing and cross-bearing is not easy to hear or follow in our day, but with the Spirit's help, we can live out that call and the world might just be transformed by it.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing was a positive outlet for my competitive tendencies. I learned the value of sportsmanship and of striving for excellence. My best friends from that period of my life were in Bible Quizzing and many of my role models for the Christian life were also part of my Quizzing world. Quizzing was also often the only Bible reading and study I did during the week, and I am thankful that I had that programmed into my weekly routine.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I learned not only how to memorize Scripture, but was able to use many of those same skills as I went on to medical school. Self-disciplines learned from those years of study and teamwork continue to serve me well. Many of the friends I made during my quizzing years continue to be encouragements to me and role models of the Christian walk.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>In college, I helped coach and quizmaster at several tournaments and have done so randomly since then.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>My wife, four children, and I are finishing our first term with Free Methodist World Missions in Mexico City, Mexico. I am a Family Physician, and we are a part of a larger team effort to see our Mexico City neighborhood reached for Christ. Prior to coming to Mexico City, I worked in a medical clinic serving the homeless population of downtown Indianapolis.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Kenneth Kaufmann" inducted="2008" participated="1965-1968" church="Greenville Free Methodist Church" city="Greenville" state="IL" image="k_kaufmann.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Meeting heroes of the faith:</answer>
			<answer>Meeting Jim Johnson, missionary kid, and his parents Warren and Jean Johnson, missionaries to South Africa, whom we later worked under in Natal-Transkei 1976-1980, at Winona Youth Advance 1965</answer>
			<answer>Meeting Youth leaders and quizmasters: Ray Bates, Ralph Park, John Baker, Robert Neil, and Robert Crandall</answer>
			<answer>Meeting Mamie Matson, retired Christian college professor, and her niece, Ruth Matson, worker at Free Methodist headquarters - their friendship of young teenagers, constant interest in us, our quiz team, and encouragement to us, which continued into adult life, even after we went to the mission field was a constant inspiration in our Christian life</answer>
			<answer>Meeting bishops and other leaders of the church</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Central Illinois Conference Champions 1966-1968</answer>
			<answer>1966 Winona Youth Advance International Bible Quiz Runnerup (2nd Place)</answer>
			<answer>1968 Midwest (Camp Mack) Regional Champion</answer>
			<answer>1968 Winona Lake International Bible Quiz Champions</answer>
			<answer>1966 and 1967 Winona Youth Advance International Bible Quiz All Star Quizzer</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>1966 - Luke 9:23 - And he said to them all, If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross daily, and follow me.</answer>
			<answer>1967 - Acts 1:8 - But ye shall receive power, after that the Holy Ghost is come upon you: and ye shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem and in all Judaea, and in Samaria, and unto the uttermost part of the earth.</answer>
			<answer>1968 - John 10:10 - The thief cometh not, but for to steal, and to kill, and to destroy: I am come that they might have life, and that they might have it more abundantly.</answer>
			<answer>John 3:30 - He must increase, but I must decrease.</answer>
			<answer>These verses reflect the teaching under which I grew up, calling for a denial of self, growing more like Christ, and living the holy life, which is possible through the Holy Spirit by means of entire sanctification, a righteousness which is from God by faith (Philippians 3:9). It is my prayer that through my life, while I decrease Christ may increase (John 3:30), that I may be crucified with Christ so that Christ may live in me (Galatians 2:20), so that people may see Christ, and come to know Him as Lord and Savior. I feel privileged that He has called us, my wife and I, to serve Him in the uttermost part of the earth, and we have enjoyed over thirty years of service in medical missions, the pastoral ministry, church planting, Christian and pastoral education, and leadership in South Africa and the Middle East.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>The excitement of the competition gave me a passion to study God's Word and to excel. It provided a focus for studying God's word and the motivation to memorize large chunks of Luke and Acts and in 1968 the whole of the Gospel of John</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It contributed to a life long passion for the study of God's Word and the sharing of the Good News.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I helped to coach: Greenville Free Methodist Church 1968-69 through 1970-71. I helped the Illinois-Wisconsin Conf quizmaster: 1972-73 through 1973-74</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>1976- 1992 - missionary Free Methodist Church of North America</answer>
			<answer>1976-1984 - Greenville Mission Hospital</answer>
			<answer>1976-1979 - Medical Doctor</answer>
			<answer>1979-1984 - Medical Superintendent</answer>
			<answer>1985-1989 - church planter, Zululand District, Natal-Transkei Conference</answer>
			<answer>1985-1986 - Medical Superintendent, Hlabisa Hospital, Hlabisa, Natal</answer>
			<answer>1986-1989 - Medical Superintendent, Benedictine Hospital, Nongoma, Natal</answer>
			<answer>1990-1992 - church planter, Pietermaritzburg, Natal-Transkei Conference</answer>
			<answer>1992-present - pastor, Northern KwaZulu-Natal Conference, Free Methodist Church in Southern Africa</answer>
			<answer>1992-2004 - Benedictine Mission Hospital</answer>
			<answer>1992-1994 - Principal Medical Officer - Obstetrics-Gynecology</answer>
			<answer>1994-1999 - Acting Medical Superintendent</answer>
			<answer>1999-2002 - District Medical Officer, Usuthu Health District</answer>
			<answer>2002-2004 - District Manager, Usuthu Health District</answer>
			<answer>1992-1996 - pastor and church planter, Nongoma-Jozini District</answer>
			<answer>1996-2004 - Conference Superintendent</answer>
			<answer>2004-present - missionary to Bahrain</answer>
			<answer>2004-present - Chief of Medical Staff, American Mission Hospital</answer>
			<answer>Taught and organized ordination classes for (Natal-Transkei) Northern and Southern KwaZulu-Natal and Eastern Cape Conferences 1979-2004 </answer>
			<answer>Presently while serving as the Chief of Medical Staff at American Mission Hospital in Bahrain, my wife and I are studying Arabic, and Islamic religion and culture. We are also studying Islam through the Zwemer Center for Muslim Studies, Columbia International University, Columbia, South Carolina by means of a distance learning part-time program. We are involved in an Arabic church, chapel services at the hospital, and in Bible studies.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Mike Hopper" inducted="2008" participated="1976-1979" church="West Morris Street Free Methodist Church" city="Indianapolis" state="IN" image="m_hopper.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>I memorized Galatians, Ephesians, Philippians, Colossians, Romans, James, and John.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>At Bible Quiz Finals, our team placed 2nd in STV-A in 1977, and won the championship in STV-A in 1978, and I was top point scorer at Quiz Finals in 1978 and 1979.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>All Scripture is God-breathed and is useful for teaching, rebuking, correcting and training in righteousness, so that the man of God may be thoroughly equipped for every good work." (II Timothy 3:16-17) The Bible is God's unique and inspired word and provides guidance for every area of my life.</answer>
			<answer>Jesus said, "Do you not say, 'Four months more and then the harvest?' I tell you, open your eyes and look at the fields! They are ripe for harvest." (John 4:35) (See also Matthew 9:36-38.) My calling to ministry centers upon introducing unbelievers to Jesus Christ, and the time to do that is not later, but now! Also, a primary focus for my ministry has been to "harvest dedicated workers and leaders for Christ."</answer>
			<answer>Now to Him who is able to do immeasurably more than all we ask or imagine, according to His power that is at work within us, to Him be glory in the church and in Christ Jesus throughout all generations, for ever and ever! Amen." (Ephesians 3:20-21) This passage reminds me that God can do greater things in and through me than I can even imagine, and one key to this is for me to be totally open and committed to God.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing provided me spiritual growth: Were it not for my three years of quizzing as a teen, I doubt I would be a Christian today and certainly not serving the Lord as a pastor. Those quizzing years were a time of great spiritual growth in my life, and the scriptures learned then still come to mind and guide my life today. </answer>
			<answer>Quizzing provided me with many friendships: Many of my best friends are serving in the ministry of Bible Quizzing. Our common desire to see youth grow spiritually through studying and applying God's word and the opportunity to visit at monthly tournaments has helped develop and sustain those relationships.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Quizzing provided me with a wife: While I was attending Asbury Seminary and directing quizzing for the Kentucky-Tennessee Conference, at regional tournaments I met a wonderful quiz coach from Hookstown, PA who later became my wife. </answer>
			<answer>Quizzing provided meaningful discipleship for my children: All three of my children competed at least 6 years in quizzing and learned and memorized many scriptures. While four national championships were won by them, what will last is God's word that was planted in their hearts. Quizzing provided a good format for our family to study God's word together.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>Coach: 1994-1996 and 1998-2008 - Coached the Fillmore (MN) teams.</answer>
			<answer>Conference Quiz Director: 1999-2008 - Director for the North Central Conference</answer>
			<answer>Denominational Director: (15 years) In 1999-2002 - Denominational Co-Director (teamed up with Mark Colgan); in 2002-2006 - Denominational Director; and in 2006-2008 - Denominational Co-Director (teamed up with Eric Young)	</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Pastoring a growing, vibrant congregation in Fillmore, MN. Retiring Denominational Director of Bible Quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Richard Snyder" inducted="2007" participated="1956-1957" church="Elmira Free Methodist Church" city="Elmira" state="NY" image="r_snyder.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>We took second in the Susquehanna finals, beat out by Syracuse (which placed 2nd in the nation). My mom was the coach.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>My favorite verse in John is "The Word became flesh and lived for a while among us. We have seen His glory, the glory of the only Son, who came from the Father, full of grace and truth." (John 1:14) My life theme verse is "I want to know Christ and the power of His resurrection and the fellowship of sharing in his sufferings, becoming like Him in His death, and so, somehow, to attain to the resurrection from the dead." (Philippians 3:10)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>When I took the Gospel of John From Dr. Stanley Magill at RWC, I scored the highest grade anyone had ever had on that course. He used to tell this to students after I became Superintendent of the Genesee Conference. Later, one other student matched my grade. It remains my favorite gospel, though it's truths continue to go deeper than my understanding. Early on, Snyder made the decision to begin each day with scripture reading: "No Bible, no breakfast."</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>The Reverend Richard D. Snyder, an ordained elder in the Genesee Conference, was elected to the office of bishop of the Free Methodist church on October 22, 1991 during the annual meeting of the North America General Conference's Board of Administration at Indianapolis, Indiana. He serves as overseer of the Eastern Area conferences: Genesee, Great Britain, Gulf Cost, Keystone, Maryland-Virginia, New England, New South, New York, Ireland, South Atlantic, and Susquehanna. He also oversees the work in continental Europe. Dr. Snyder is an alumnus of Roberts Wesleyan College (Rochester, New York) and McMaster Divinity School (Hamilton, Ontario). He has been a member of the Roberts Wesleyan College Board of Trustees since 1989, serving on the Long Range Planning Committee until October 1991 when he was named to the Academic Affairs Committee. He has been a member of the College Ministerial Advisory Board since 1981. Roberts Wesleyan College conferred an honorary doctorate degree on the Bishop in 1998.</answer>
			<answer>Bishop Snyder was ordained as deacon in 1965 and elder in 1967. He pastored for two years in the Canada Great Lakes Conference and 14 years in the Genesee Conference. He was elected superintendent of the Genesee Conference in 1979 and held that office until July 1991 when he was elected superintendent of the Susquehanna Conference.</answer>
			<answer>He has been a member of the North America General Conference's Board of Administration since 1979 and has a distinguished record of service to that body. He chaired the former Commission on Evangelism and Church Growth from 1985-1989 and the former Administrative Commission from 1989 to 1991.</answer>
			<answer>Says Bishop Snyder: "I wish every church would develop a quizzing ministry because the Word of God is SO powerful and we live in a society that is mostly ignorant regarding the Word of God. I think the quizzers have a huge advantage in life because they have studied and memorized and reflected on the Word of God."</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Dolores Bailes" inducted="2007" participated="1955-2005" church="Oakland Free Methodist Church" city="East Liverpool" state="OH" image="d_bailes.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>(Heaven - March 10, 2006) (formerly of Georgetown, PA)</answer>
			<answer>During the years of 1955 to 2005, Dolores coached teams from Monaca, PA; Sylvan Crest, PA; Hookstown, PA; Chester, WV; and East Liverpool (Oakland), OH. She started coaching back when they had jump judges and not electric quiz chairs. Dolores actively coached until October 2007 when a stroke put her in the hospital, but even then she still asked the kids quiz questions when the came to visit. According to daughter Sheila, "The biggest difference quizzing made in her life was knowing the scriptures. She didn't need a concordance; she was it. She enjoyed coaching her own children and grandchildren, and watching kids memorize Bible verses and seeing it change their lives." Dolores served as the Pittsburgh Conference Bible Quiz Promoter for several years (about 1975 -1980). Her favorite scripture was Philippians 4:13: "I can do everything through Him who gives me strength."</answer>
			<answer>A Tribute about Dolores Bailes by Rev. Michael Hopper Free Methodist Denominational Co-Director of Bible Quizzing</answer>
			<answer>King David wrote: "How can a young man keep his way pure? By living according to Your word. I seek You with all my heart; do not let me stray from Your commands. I have hidden Your word in my heart that I might not sin against You....I rejoice in following Your statutes as one rejoices in great riches. I meditate on Your precepts and consider Your ways. I delight in Your decrees...." (Psalm 119:9-16)</answer>
			<answer>As I think of Dolores Bailes, these words from Psalm 119 come to mind. Having known her since 1983, I can tell you that Dolores had a deep love for God and for His word. She delighted in the Holy Scriptures.</answer>
			<answer>About six months ago, I called Dolores to ask her about her experiences with Bible Quizzing. One of my first questions was to ask her if she ever quizzed as a teen. She told me: "I was too old to quiz" and explained that it wasn't until 1951 (when she was 21 years old) that she invited Christ into her life as her Lord and Savior. (Quizzing back then was for those up to age 20.)</answer>
			<answer>Dolores then proceeded to tell me about some of the joys that she had in encouraging teens to study God's word. She started coaching a quiz team around 1956 in Monaca, PA, and then told me: "Ever since then, I have always had a team-except for 1-2 years when I was not coaching." She also coached youth in Hookstown, PA; Chester, WV; and East Liverpool (Oakland), OH. She recounted the days when the Free Methodist denominational Quiz Finals were held at Camp Mack in Winona Lake, Indiana.</answer>
			<answer>Around 1957, Dolores worked at the Free Methodist Headquarters with Earnest Keasling, the Director of Free Methodist Youth Ministries, with a specific focus on the denominational youth magazine: "Youth in Action." Keasling was the one who originally started Free Methodist Bible Quizzing, and perhaps her association with him further encouraged her interest in and love for God's word.</answer>
			<answer>Not only did Dolores have the desire for the youth of her local church to learn God's word, but she also encouraged the other coaches and teams of the Pittsburgh Conference. For a period of about 4-5 years, she served as the Quiz Director for the Conference.</answer>
			<answer>One of the greatest blessings that Dolores brought to me was my wife. As a young adult, Janet (Crawford) Hopper attended the Hookstown Church and was invited to serve along with Howard and Dolores in ministering to the teens. The Bailes mentored Janet and trained her to be a leader. As time went on, they thought it would be good for her to be married to a minister, and knew of one (me) who was attending Asbury Theological Seminary in Wilmore, KY. Howard and Dolores (along with one of Dolores' former quizzers Evie Smith) encouraged this relationship through inviting me up to tournaments and providing housing in their home. Janet and I were married in 1984, and what a blessing Janet has been to me and my ministry. I thank God for the way Howard and Dolores Bailes invested in her.</answer>
			<answer>One of the greatest joys for Dolores was to be able to encourage her own children in studying God's word through coaching them in Bible Quizzing, and then many years later to coach her own grandchildren. She was delighted to be able to tell me: "Most of my grandchildren have quizzed....Quizzing is the best program....You can't do anything better." Dolores had a deep love for God and for His word. In a humble way, Dolores ended our conversation by telling me that one of the greatest blessings of Bible Quizzing was that "I really know the Bible, especially the New Testament." I appreciate the way that Debbie Teter, Dolores' daughter, has put it: "Mom lived her life studying the Book; now she gets to be with the Author."</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Jay Vincent" inducted="2007" participated="1981-1987" church="Island and North Anderson Free Methodist Churches" city="Island, North Anderson" state="IL, IN" image="j_vincent.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1986 - STR National Championship</answer>
			<answer>One national finalist in individuals. 2 conference individual championships. National finalist for team 3 times.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Though I am free and belong to no man, I make myself a slave to everyone, to win as many as possible. To the Jews I became like a Jew, to win the Jews. To those under the law I became like one under the law (though I myself am not under the law), so as to win those under the law. To those not having the law I became like one not having the law (though I am not free from God's law but am under Christ's law), so as to win those not having the law. To the weak I became weak, to win the weak. I have become all things to all men so that by all possible means I might save some. I do all this for the sake of the gospel, that I may share in its blessings. Do you not know that in a race all the runners run, but only one gets the prize? Run in such a way as to get the prize. Everyone who competes in the games goes into strict training. They do it to get a crown that will not last; but we do it to get a crown that will last forever. Therefore I do not run like a man running aimlessly; I do not fight like a man beating the air. No, I beat my body and make it my slave so that after I have preached to others, I myself will not be disqualified for the prize." (I Corinthians 9:19-27) Paul's lifelong passion was to save some and keep himself pure. In life we have many goals, aspirations and accomplishment, but none more important than Paul's defined purpose.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I am a living, breathing example of Isaiah's claim that the Word of God will not return null and void. Throughout my teen years I tended to want to wander away from God and church, but quizzing kept me near. As much as I wanted to do other things I liked quizzing better. Remaining in the Word kept me grounded and near God even when I didn't want to.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>The Scripture never leaves. The knowledge of Scripture has helped over and over in ministry. With the foundation of Bible quizzing I have gained great respect for God's Word. It has become one of my greatest pasions: teaching others the love and appreciate Scripture.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I pastored for 15 years in the Free Methodist Church.</answer>
			<answer>I have served as the Mideast Regional Quiz Director and Wabash Conference Director. Currently I am coaching the YTR team from Aldersgate.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Mark Scandrett" inducted="2007" participated="1971-1972" church="Iowa City Free Methodist Church" city="Iowa City" state="IA" image="m_scandrett.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>My experience was so limited that I didn't have any highlights. Actually, most of my quizzing was in the 1971-72 year, when I was too young to legally quiz. (Back then it was just for high school students.) But they let me quiz in a couple of matches (not tournaments) with other churches, and although I wasn't eligible to quiz in the conference championship, our team won and competed at Finals at IYC that summer. Back then, only conference champions were eligible for Finals. Probably the highlight for me was memorizing the book of Galatians - I felt like I had really accomplished something.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Carry each other's burdens, and in this way you will fulfill the law of Christ." (Galatians 6:2) This verse taught me a lesson that is a big part of my life as pastor - that as a follower of Christ I have a responsibility to help carry the burdens of others as they go through hard times.</answer>
			<answer>I have coached Bible quizzing since 1983 - for two years as a seminarian at Wilmore, KY, and for 22 years here in Alton, IL. More recently, I've turned over head coaching responsibilities to others but have continued to serve as assistant coach and quizmaster at tournaments. In recent years, I've also served as Midwest Region Bible Quiz Director. I've promoted quizzing at Annual Conference, in local churches and at youth camps. As coach, I've committed to memorizing (now re-memorizing) the Scripture with our quizzers, and I've enjoyed participating in QUIC quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Although I wasn't involved much in quizzing due to the fact that our church only had a quiz team for a short time, I was blessed by the Scripture I learned and by being introduced to the discipline of Scripture memorization. This early exposure to quizzing was a positive experience for me and paved the way for my later involvement as an adult leader.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Quizzing has motivated me to memorize over 2/3 of the New Testament. Having the Scripture deeply ingrained in my mind and heart has been a tremendous tool for ministry and has made it much easier for me to know God's will. I have found quizzing to be a great discipleship tool and have used it in the discipleship development of many young people, a good number of whom are now leaders in our congregation. All three of my children have participated in quizzing, and I greatly appreciate the spiritual growth and deepened commitment to Christ that they have experienced through quizzing. I am a natural coach - I love to bring out the best in others! I have received a lot of satisfaction from helping young people do well in quizzing. A highlight for me was coaching my sons Nathan and Matthew when their team won the Alpha-Omega trophy. Even more satisfying is seeing these young people grow in their relationship with Christ. Quizzing has been a great way to use my gift of coaching.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Senior pastor at Emmanuel FMC in Alton, IL and Mid-West Regional Bible Quiz Director</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Penny Norton" inducted="2007" participated="1991-present" church="Brockport Free Methodist Church" city="Brockport" state="NY" image="p_norton.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>I began my involvement with quizzing in about 1991 when I was Youth Leader at the Allegany Free Methodist church. My husband actually started the team there and I occassionally was able to go and help at practice and quizzes. The next year I began quiz mastering. When we moved to Brockport I became a coach there almost as fast as my boys joined the team. I've since become head coach. At the monthly quizzes I coach a team or quiz master depending on where the need is. I've also quiz mastered at Finals numerous times.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing as an adult?">
			<answer>Memorizing the Sermon on the Mount</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Do not merely listen to the word, and so deceive yourselves. Do what it says." (James 1:22) It's been a favorite for a long time because it reminds me that I don't read and learn Scripture just to gain to knowledge, but to become more like Christ, and that takes action.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>God is still guiding me through quizzing. A few years ago He called me into full time ministry at Quiz Finals (and we thought those appeals were just for the teens), and I am going through the learning process to become a pastor now.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Along with Bible Quizzing I am involved in a ministry called Stitching Servants which makes blankets, hats, mittens, etc for the homeless or others in need. We want to reach out in Jesus' name as Dorcas did. I teach two years olds in the church's preschool - an outreach program. And I am a community leader for our small groups, providing encouragement and guidance to small groups leaders.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Dawn McCoon" inducted="2006" participated="1961, 1965-1966" church="Pontiac Free Methodist Church" city="Clarkson" state="MI" image="d_mccoon.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>I loved studying Acts. I also loved watching the Jump Quizzing competition that was held during Camp and Conference at the East Michigan Camp ground.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>I found Acts 1:7-8 a comfort when people would try to say that the end was coming at such and such a time. And I would claim verse 8 knowing that the Holy Sprit's power was with me especially when I would witness to my friends. Since I have been coaching quizzing I have found that Romans 8:23 is there when I don't know how I should pray, because the word promises that the Sprit intercedes for us when we can't express ourselves with words.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I found that studying the Word of God was actually fun and I loved the competition.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I have learned how to use scripture in my everyday life. I have learned that you have to actually study the word of God--not just memorize it. It is good to have scripture memorized, but if we never learn what it means and how to apply it to our daily walk, it will return void. I learned through Matthew 25:1-13 that you should never give up walking the way God instructs or you may be left behind. Don't get caught without oil in your lamp.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Besides being the head coach at the Clarkston (MI) Free Methodist Church and the Co-Director for the conference, I work with the High School teens on Wednesday night and am in charge of a small group. My husband and I are also on the leadership team for one of our Adult Bible Fellowship groups on Sunday morning.</answer>
			<answer>I am currently the head coach at the Clarkston FMC and Co-Director of the East Michigan Conference Bible Quiz ministry.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Lyle McCoon" inducted="2006" participated="1961, 1965-1966" church="Pontiac Free Methodist Church" city="Pontiac" state="MI" image="l_mccoon.jpg">
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>My favorite scripture from Romans is Chapter 12:1-2. I like this passage because it tells me that what we do on earth should be as a "living sacrifice" and that we should not be concerned what the world says we should do with our lives</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>While I did not quiz as a teen I have seen the affects of quizzing on teens at our church. I remember a Sunday school teacher once told me how impressed he was with knowledge the young teen quizzers had of the Bible book he was teaching from. He said he never realized that quizzers studied the Bible to the depth of knowledge they had.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>My first involvement with quizzing was when my son, Lyle, Jr. was in the eighth grade. He wanted to go to Quiz Nationals, but no one at our church could go. He and I went to Nationals together. I saw how much the quizzers knew and how they were using it in their lives. I decided that quizzing was a ministry that I should help in. I learn along with the quizzers as we study God's word and they get involved with the competition.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I drive buses for Church activities. I assist with leadership of our Adult Bible Fellowship (Sunday school). I teach Adult Bible Fellowship (Sunday school) classes as needed. I am a substitute sound technician. I am co-chair of the Church Board of Trustees. I occasionally teach the High School class on Wednesday evenings. I work with a small group of High School students on Wednesday evenings.</answer>
			<answer>At the present time I am fairly involved with Bible Quizzing in the following ways: I am co-director of Bible Quizzing for the East Michigan Conference. I repair quiz sets at conference, regional and national quiz meets. During Quiz practices at our church I lead in-depth Bible studies.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Greg Fields" inducted="2006" participated="1984-1990" church="McPherson Free Methodist Church" city="McPherson" state="KS" image="g_fields.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Finally becoming good friends with the Bedford team. Quizzing side by side with my lifelong best friend - Ryan Joy. Winning the Spit Shine Award the year we didn't study like we should have. Endless hours of quoting scripture to my mom and dad.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Team:</answer>
			<answer>1985 - 1st young teen veteran</answer>
			<answer>1989 - 1st senior teen veteran</answer>
			<answer>1990 - 1st senior teen veteran</answer>
			<answer>Individual</answer>
			<answer>1990 - 1st senior teen veteran</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Matthew 22:37-40. This is where Jesus told the Pharisees that loving God and loving our neighbors are what all of the commandments revolve around. It simplifies a lot of scripture. It reminds me that I have to put away all my pride and think about first of all pleasing God and loving Him, and then showing His love to those around me. I can use this verse to check my own actions by determining if my motives are to benefit myself or to bring glory to God by loving Him and/or others.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>My sophomore year was the first year that I started memorizing the entire portion word for word. That year my grades in school went from a B - C average to straight A's. I felt like I was able to retain any information I saw or heard much easier when I was memorizing scripture. More importantly than my grades though, quizzing helped ground me in my faith. Middle school and High school are difficult years and there were many times when I felt the world calling me away from the Lord. I was definitely not perfect throughout these years, but I know that there were many good decisions that I made only because I had God's word in my heart. I also knew that I was being held accountable by my fellow quizzers.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Quizzing gave me a great foundation in the scripture. I am amazed to see how many life-long church goers really don't know a lot about what God says to us in His word. I probably wouldn't have either if I hadn't been in Quizzing. I am in sales now, and I know that quizzing helped give me confidence to get up in front of people. It also gave me confidence in myself to know that when we are diligent about something and work at it with all of our strength, God will reward us - even if it's not in the way we expected. Hard work pays off, and God will reward those who work hard for Him.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>My wife and I teach 3rd Grade Sunday School at the McPherson Free Methodist church (helping with some future champion quizzers). We also lead the 5th Grade class on Wednesday nights. I have served on various committees at the church for the last several years and am currently on the board of Elyria Christian School close to McPherson. I enjoy singing whenever I can to praise our Lord.  I have helped in some way with the quiz ministry at McPherson since I returned to live there in 1994.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="James Setty" inducted="2006" participated="1957-1959" church="Harvey Free Methodist Church" city="Harvey" state="IL" image="j_setty.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>We met once a week at someone's home for practice, study, and fellowship. We only quizzed against other churches once or twice during the year. Our conference finals were at Camp Epworth in Belvidere, Illinois. Rev. W. R. Thompson was our pastor and quiz coach. He wrote all of his own materials. I enjoyed spending time with my friends, going to camps, and quizzing against other teams.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1958 - International Bible Quiz Championship at Camp Mack, near Winona Lake, Indiana. We studied the book of Genesis (all 52 chapters). We quizzed against the Winona Lake team in the final round and won.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Genesis really didn't give me a favorite scripture but one of my favorite scriptures from the Old Testament is Proverbs 3:5. God is a lot smarter than I am. He has always provided for me, both spiritually and materially. I can see how the Lord has directed my life in providing a marriage partner, raising my children, and keeping me in a church where I have been able to serve Him.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It gave me an incentive to read the Bible. Once I got started, I wanted to know more. I associated mostly with Christian young people, which helped me to live a Christian life. Quizzing gave me confidence in myself.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I met my wife, Meredith, through being involved in Free Methodist youth activities. Meredith was also a quizzer in the FM church in Melrose Park, Illinois. Also, I have enjoyed lasting friendships with many people as a quizzer and coach.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How have you been involved in quizzing since you were a quizzer?">
			<answer>We have had quiz programs in the past. In 1969, when I was in the Army in Fairbanks, Alaska, my wife and I organized our first quiz team at the Fairbanks First Church of the Nazarene. We coached 4 or 5 young people. One of the members of that team has gone on to be a very active quizzing organizer for the Nazarene denomination and has had many years of success in quizzing. His children are now active in quizzing under his coaching. In the 1970's we had a team, and in 1987-88 we had a team with my two children were involved with two other team members. We started our current quiz program in Monee, IL in 2002. I am amazed at what the Lord has done for our young people through this program. We started with a group of kids from three difference schools who were not very close to each other and now we have a group of close friends. The parents have commented that the quiz program has done so much for their kids. These kids are now becoming members of our church and are looking forward to coaching someday. What a miracle!!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am currently our local church delegate to the North Central Conference, Sunday morning worship song leader, on our local Board of Administration, substitute teacher for the adult and teen Sunday School classes, and quiz coach.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Marvin Earl Gray" inducted="2006" participated="1983-1989" church="McPherson Free Methodist Church" city="McPherson" state="KS" image="m_gray.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Lots of road-trips; memorizing all of James, John, Hebrews, 1 and 2 Peter, and Matthew, and some of the other books; singing "So go on and quiz out, good bye bye bye good bye" at Spring Arbor Nationals Awards Banquet with Dan Koehn, Ryan Joy, and Greg Fields in 1987; staying up all night with friends after the awards banquet; pleasing coaches Greg and Nancy Gossell; and Bruce's bad buffalo bonus quiz questionables.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1988 - We placed 2nd at Greenville over Hebrews 1 and 2 Peter in 1988. It was my first quiz that year, as I'd been in the Dominican Republic with VISA all year.</answer>
			<answer>As a 7th grader over Romans and James in 1984, I was the 5th highest points per question in at Bible Quiz Finals. I was the "Coach of the Year" in the Pacific Northwest Conference in 1995.</answer>
			<answer>I have coached for 8 years, and been at 11 of the last 20 Nationals. I have coached at least 5 1st place teams at our regional tournament, and a 5th place team at nationals. I love to QUiC Quiz.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It gave me something to work on and work for. It filled a lot of time I would have wasted otherwise. It helped me to know and understand God's word much more deeply. It helped cement life-long friendships.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I still get thrills and chills about QUiC (adult) quizzing; and I love to Quizmaster and make it fun but excellent. I quote scripture (that I have memorized or reviewed recently) often in ministry and teaching. I love to read and study the Bible and to inspire my own children to do the same.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am a community pastor at Seattle's Rainier Avenue Free Methodist Church. I lead a men's recovery group. I help raise up and train leaders in our local church and neighborhood. I teach at Seattle Pacific University as an adjunct faculty member. I have been working at Operation Nightwatch, referring homeless clients to shelter. I am loving my wife Julie and 4 children Maria, Daniel, Rachel, and Melody.</answer>
			<answer>I am a coach, quizmaster, and quiz parent.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Dale Martin" inducted="2005" participated="1955-1958" church="Winona Lake Free Methodist Church" city="Winona Lake" state="IN" image="d_martin.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Attending Youth Camp at Camp Mack in northern Indiana; meeting other quizzers; having Florence Murray, a retired missionary, as our coach.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1956 - 3rd place (Romans)</answer>
			<answer>1957 - 1st place, International Bible Quiz Champions (John) - first year the electric chairs were used</answer>
			<answer>1958 - 2nd place (Genesis)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing gave a focus to our summer, and helped develop concentration and dedication, spurred on by the challenge of competition.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It has given me a high regard for scripture and its importance, as well as an understanding of the value of memorization so that the Word is close at hand.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I've taught at Greenville College for 38 years and am active in our local FM church.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Doug Whitlock" inducted="2005" participated="1991-1998" church="Knox Knolls Free Methodist Church" city="Springfield" state="IL" image="d_whitlock.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>(Heaven)</answer>
			<answer>The following comes from a letter from Doug's mother, Karen Whitlock:</answer>
			<answer>Doug quizzed from 1991 to 1998. He started when he was in the sixth grade. He quizzed for the Knox Knolls Free Methodist Church in Springfield, IL in the Gateway Conference. In 1993, our Young Teen Veteran team took first place at nationals. Herb Coates was the coach, and others on the team were Crecia Keithley, Michelle Barth, Greg Coates, and Bryan Vollintine. In 1998, Doug took first place in Senior Teen Individuals.</answer>
			<answer>Doug was passionate about quizzing. He was that way about everything he did. If he thought it was worth doing, he gave it his all. Travis Peterson, in his eulogy at Doug's funeral, said that Doug still had most of the New Testament memorized. Travis said that no matter what subject was under discussion, Doug could come up with an appropriate quote.</answer>
			<answer>I think that quizzing also help set him on the road to regular Bible study. In an article he wrote for our conference newsletter, he said, "When I was involved in Bible Quizzing, my study was for memorization. In those times I would study intensely and read and reread passages in order to remember them. This worked very well. As I read for personal meditation, however, I use a different approach. First I like to have an extended plan of what I will be studying. This usually includes a certain book or two to be read over a month or so. Then, as I do my reading, I try to read in sections rather than two or three verses. This gives more continuity to my study and imparts some context to the individual verses. Then I can see the whole picture of what a verse is saying. Each reading is a blessing and a joy."</answer>
			<answer>The other thing that kept Doug interested in quizzing was the relationships he developed there. He especially enjoyed the Decatur boys, including Travis Peterson and Dustin Fenton, and the Greenville girls, including Rebekkah Krober, Kristin Markell, Courtney Summerville, and Annie Catron. They all were about the same age, and they had a healthy, friendly rivalry, but they were also all good friends.</answer>
			<answer>After high school, Doug sometimes went to quizzes as a quizmaster. While he was attending the University of Illinois at Champaign for two years, he coached the quiz team at the Mattis Avenue Free Methodist Church. When he moved back to Springfield, he started coaching the quiz team at our church. This shows his belief in the value of quizzing.</answer>
			<answer>Doug was very active in his home church in Springfield. He was elected as reserve delegate to annual conference. He was serving as quiz coach and church treasurer, and had a seat on the Official Board. He was a worship leader, sometimes playing the piano, but most often singing on the worship team. He would often closely question us about the lyrics of songs and their theological implications. He didn't want to sing anything that was not appropriate Scripturally.</answer>
			<answer>After Doug's death, one man in our church talked about Doug being "wise beyond his years." I think it was the deep knowledge of the Scripture that he gained through Bible Quizzing that accounted for this maturity.</answer>
			<answer>Former pastor Herb Coates wrote: "Doug Whitlock, 24, of the Knox Knolls (Springfield, IL) Free Methodist Church was killed Sunday evening (May 22, 2005) when his motorcycle was hit by a car. This year he has been coaching the Springfield team. He also coached the Mattis Avenue Free Methodist Church quiz team of Champaign, IL while he was getting his engineering degree from the University of Illinois. He was with his quiz team from Springfield at the West Morris Street quiz the day before his death."</answer>
			<answer>Doug's former youth pastor Steve Coates wrote: "During a Sunday morning worship service in Springfield, I asked several high school teens to share a favorite verse with the congregation. Doug selected and quoted 2 Corinthians 7:1: "Since we have these promises, dear friends, let us purify ourselves from everything that contaminates body and spirit, perfecting holiness out of reverence for God." Yes, let us do so, not only because of the promises, but because of their fulfillment in our lifetime in the life of Doug."</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Lyle McCoon, Jr." inducted="2005" participated="1985-1991" church="Pontiac and Clarkston Free Methodist Church" city="Pontiac,Clarkston" state="MI" image="l_mccoonjr.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Rededicating my life to Christ for the first time at the Communion service at Nationals after my 9th grade year; getting to go to 5 Nationals at 4 different Free Methodist colleges; quizzing with and against many future close friends including my future wife, Dawn Bosworth.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>My team was East Michigan Conference champs in 1990 and 1991 in STV; at Nationals, however, no; sadly, the closest we came was a 3rd place finish in STR in Seattle in 1989. Individually, I was the East Michigan Conference champ in 1988, 1989, 1990, and 1991; at Nationals, the closest I came was in 1988 when I finished 2nd at Greenville in YT Individuals and in 1989 when I finished 4th in Seattle in ST Individuals.</answer>
			<answer>I was captain of the Senior Team All-Star Team at Nationals in 1989, 1990, and 1991, quizzing out every round of Nationals all three years.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>My favorite passage was always 2 Corinthians 4:7-9. I loved the imagery of the passage, and it was a source of encouragment to me to continue living an overt and openly Christian life in my public high school.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It completely rearranged my attitudes. I was quite stuck on myself as a young teen, and success in quizzing fed my arrogance. What I did not realize is that the Scripture I was memorizing was working on my heart, even if I did not realize it. It all came together at the Communion service at Nationals in Greenville after my 9th grade year when I realized how messed up I was and rededicated my life to Christ. After that, my attitudes changed greatly and I became far more ministry minded, receiving a call to full-time ministry the following year.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Quizzing's influence on my life is immeasurable. I am literally the person I am today because of quizzing. Through its motivation to memorize Scripture, quizzing has continued to impact my life every year that I have participated (20 years now).</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am an ordained elder in the Free Methodist Church. I have served local churches as pastor for 9 years. I am also pursuing a doctorate in New Testament (working on the book of James) with a view to teaching Bible and theology in a Christian college or seminary. I currently fill in preaching as needed, teach a Sunday School class, and give leadership to the Nicholasville (KY) Open Door Free Methodist Church.</answer>
			<answer>I am currently the conference director for the New South Conference as well as the national question writer for the C level quiz questions. In addition, I have for the past several years written the Junior questions for the Pacific Northwest. The following is a summation of my quizzing participation since graduating high school: head coach of Greenville, IL (1991-1995); conference director of Gateway Conference (1996-1999); regional director over Gateway, North Central, Great Plains, etc. (1998-2000); head coach of Quincy, IL (1999-2000); conference director of New South Conference (2000-present); head coach of Open Door, Nicholasville, KY (2000-2003).</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Peter Samuelson" inducted="2005" participated="1980-1986" church="McPherson and Winona Lake Free Methodist Church" city="McPherson, Winona Lake" state="KS, IN" image="p_samuelson.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>I have many wonderful memories of quizzing. I'm very competitive, so the competition was certainly fun - and the winning was enjoyable. Much longer-lasting were the friendships I made with fellow quizzers across the US - many of whom I kept in close touch with for years afterwards. I had some great teammates - and many good memories of quizzing with them - including my teammates Dan Koehn (who memorized the material more thoroughly than anyone else I ever knew), with whom I quizzed for McPherson; one of my college roommates, Kevin Kwilinski, who quizzed for Winona Lake, and his wife Amy (Starr) Kwilinski, who quizzed for Kalamazoo, and Bryan and Wes Blankenship and Kurt Gerrild, all of whom quizzed for McPherson; and Rick Gensch, who quizzed for Winona Lake (who was the fastest and best jumper I ever quizzed with or against). I'm sure I'm forgetting some others that I should name. And we had great coaches who not only taught us to win, but also modeled Christ and service in their lives - including Cathi Blankenship, Les Rice and Greg Gossell.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>4th in young teen team at IYC estes park 1981; 2nd in young teen individuals (to Rick Gensch)</answer>
			<answer>1st in young teen veteran team in 1982; 2nd in young teen individuals (to Emily Pickerel )</answer>
			<answer>2nd in senior teen veteran team in 1983 (to mary helen brown and dan sewell); 1st in young teen individuals</answer>
			<answer>1st in senior teen veteran team in 1984; 1st in senior teen individuals</answer>
			<answer>1st in senior teen veteran team in 1985 at IYC estes park; 2nd in senior teen individuals (to jim egyud, Pennsylvania)</answer>
			<answer>1st in senior teen veteran team in 1986 at central; 1st in senior teen individuals.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>That has changed over the years. Currently, it is Romans 12:2: "Do not conform any longer to the pattern of this world, but be transformed by the renewing of your mind. Then you will be able to test and approve what God's will is--His good, pleasing, and perfect will."</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It was my primary extracurricular activity. I devoted lots of time each week to studying and practice - and looked forward to the tournaments. I'm sure I made more, closer friends through quizzing (and church, generally) than I did at school, where I don't recall being that involved outside of classes.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It has had a very significant and long-lasting impact on my faith and spiritual life. And it is where I developed some of my longest lasting friendships.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Primarily through my work as President of Americans United for Life. We are a non-profit, pro-life law firm, working to restore legal protections for the sanctity of human life.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Greg Sanders" inducted="2004" participated="1971-1978" church="Greenville Free Methodist Church" city="Greenville" state="IL" image="g_sanders.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Several national championship quizzes, first as a youngster with the Kaufmann's, where I would get a question or two in each round as a "substitute," and the great challenge was simply to get something answered correctly during the questions when I was "in play," and to beat the Kaufmann's, as well as the opponents, off the chairs. Later, it was quizzing against formidable opponents such as Kevin Ready and Mike Hopper. Spiritually speaking, every year was a highlight. Each section of scripture fed my spirit, and the Lord used it to grow character within me, and to help me in my everyday decision-making. My final year, as a college freshmen was particularly significant. (They let you quiz up to age 20 back then.) For the first time, I fully memorized all of the material (I may have earlier, but was not in the habit of quoting through it from beginning to end) and quoted all of Romans and James with no mistakes in 45 minutes. (Well, there were 1 or 2 mistakes, but I had an opportunity to go back and correct them)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1974 - Senior Teen National Champion</answer>
			<answer>1976 - 2nd place - Senior Teen</answer>
			<answer>1978 - 2nd place - Senior Teen</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"But seek first His kingdom and His righteousness, and all these things will be given to you as well." (Matthew 6:33) This verse to me represented the very foundation of a life built on priorities. Kingdom priorities first, then everything else. I came back to this verse time and time again, especially as I was tempted to quit quizzing for the world of sports and high school musicals. While important, I eventually determined that nothing would take me out of quizzing, because I recognized its permanent spiritual impact on my life.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I got into quizzing because I was infatuated with a pretty, vivacious, blond-haired girl. I stayed with it because I fell in love with the Lord.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It's hard to calculate the significance that half of the New Testament bouncing around in your head can have on your decisions and priorities. First of all, the memorized word in my head becomes the meditative word in my heart and mind. Next, if the Word of God is the sword of the Spirit, and I'm 100% sure it is, then the quizzing books in my head keep the Lord's sword very sharp, and regularly prunes off branches. You would think that all of that Scripture in your head, and all of God's laws so to speak, might make life very difficult. Actually, the reverse is true. The sharper the knife, the less it hurts when the Lord trims you into shape.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How have you been involved in quizzing since you were a quizzer?">
			<answer>The year after college graduation, I got involved in quizzing as a coach. Being a youth pastor as well, I had the opportunity to acquaint many young people with the ministry of quizzing, first in Springfield, Illinois, and then in Kalamazoo and Clarkston, Michigan, respectively. While in Kalamazoo, we started a brand new quiz team, and in one year (1981-82) did something somewhat unusual for a first-year team - we took not only 1st place, but also 2nd place in the STV division at National Finals. Over the next 5 years, as not only a coach but a youth pastor interested in outreach as well as nurture, I combined our quiz team and youth choir and took them "on the road" in southern Michigan, putting on concerts, puppet shows, and demonstration Bible quizzes to other FM youth groups. Within about 3 years, we had about 12 teams started in both the South and East Michigan conferences, enough for some decent regional quizzing. Some of those teams are still active today. We also hosted a Kalamazoo Holiday Bible Quiz tournament over the Christmas holiday for 3 years, and we combined quizzing with a camp atmosphere, and I specifically remember some kids getting saved through the ministry of Sacrifice of Praise (a local music group).</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Since coming back to Greenville 13 years ago, I have been involved with the quizzing ministry, first as a helper, and in recent years as the head coach. I am continually searching for new techniques or "systems" to help teens learn the scripture more easily, and have recently written "quote verse songs," developed picture stories, and other things to help teens (and myself!) to learn the material more easily. I love quizzing, I love the teens who catch the quizzing fever, and I love the Lord who makes all things possible! It's easy to get excited about quizzing when you see the spiritual results that it brings!</answer>
			<answer>As far as other spiritual ministries are concerned, I am a professor at Greenville College, where I witness for Christ in and out of the classroom with students. Some people think it's hard to take a secular science like sociology and make it fit with Christianity, but for a former Bible quizzer whose mind is filled many nuggets of wisdom from God's Word, it's really not so hard! All wisdom comes from God, and the Scripture simply makes His truth more evident. I am also devoted to my family, to witnessing to my neighbors, and to any other opportunity I have to serve my Lord.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Julie Allman" inducted="2004" participated="1988-1994" church="New Brighton Free Methodist Church" city="New Brighton" state="PA" image="j_allman.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Some of my favorite memories of quizzing were when we had a YTV team with stiff competition from Pearce, NY and in our own conference from Highland, PA. That year or two was probably the only time I got to quiz in the 'right' division -- when we had enough people my age from our church interested in quizzing. The girls on the competing teams were excellent quizzers, and made us want to study harder and win all the more! Another highlight was staying after finals at Spring Arbor (1992 I think) with about 20 or so other Free Methodist youth -- and preparing for World Bible Quizzing together. I didn't really like World style quizzing that much, and still prefer the spirit of our National Finals, but I really enjoyed that time together with other youth from around the country.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>This may sound silly, but I really can't remember. If I were sitting with my mother and aunt, they'd quickly tell me. I guess this makes me realize what part of quizzing really lasts after the competition is over! I do remember coming in 4th place my very first year in Young Teen Individuals (I think before there was any splitting for veteran and rookie), and I was pretty excited about that. My legs hardly reached the floor that first year.</answer>
			<answer>My last year I had the honor of receiving the Dave Markell "Excellence in Attitude" award. I had memories of Dave Markell from when I was a kid too young to quiz, tagging along to Finals with my mom and dad, and I remembered his influence on the spirit of Bible quizzing. It was a special thing to receive that kind of recognition, though I know there were several others who deserved it at least as much!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>I don't have just one, but I Corinthians 1 (the whole chapter) has always been special to me. As a person who expects a lot of herself, it is always helpful for me to read those last verses to remind myself that anything significant I do will only be because of Jesus Christ. I don't have to be somebody amazing or special. I just have to let Him use me.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>As a teen, quizzing really helped to ground me in my faith - not just in opinions or popular interpretations of what the Christian life is about -- but in the living Word of God. And as I'm sure many would say the competition and just fun of quizzing itself really helped me deal with the Bible more intensely than I ever would have otherwise.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>To this day, having a Bible quizzing background helps me recall Scripture at needed times, and helps me be ready mentally to cross-reference when a certain topic comes up in Bible studies. As a missionary, I found it much easier to deal with Scripture in a foreign language since I often could find places more quickly despite the language barrier.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I'm a missionary with Free Methodist World Missions in Ukraine. I've been serving in Ukraine since 2000, working with youth, worship/music ministries, and outreach to new areas.</answer>
			<answer>I've quizmastered a few times in my own conference as well as at Nationals, but I've not been nearly as involved as I feel like I should be. We'll see however. Depending on how many years it takes for us to have our first conference of churches in Ukraine, we may see a Ukrainian Bible Quiz tournament some day!</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Kathy Costello" inducted="2004" participated="1961-1965" church="Wesleyan Methodist Church" city="Baldwinsville" state="NY" image="k_costello.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>That last year of quizzing was a most phenomenal year. I just immersed myself in the book. Any time I had free time I was studying. I do not remember memorizing like quizzers do today but yet, with all the time and analysis, the information was all there. Nationals was held at Louisville, Kentucky. Both of my teammates were boys, so I had a room all to myself that night before. There were no round robins, just one big championship quiz that Michigan and New York had gone down for. I was in the dorm room by myself. We had arrived in Kentucky that day. The excitement of travel had worn off by 9 PM so I was ready for bed and then suddenly decided to read Romans over one more time before closing my eyes. As I read it for the umpteenth time, I noticed something that I never had seen before. There were three "I beseech you (urge you) brothers." Wow! I was so excited. What a great 50 point question for question 11. At that time there were 20 questions with 15 points for easier questions and more points for more difficult questions and number 11 always being 50 points. I made sure I memorized those three verses. The next day, it happened just like it does in a story or book. It was a tight quiz with the leading score constantly swinging back and forth between Michigan and New York....that is....until question 11 when the "I beseech you" question came up. Then New York led the rest of the way.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1975 - National Champion on book of Romans</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>I would say one of my favorites is the latter part of Romans chapter 8. What powerful words.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>What an affirmation of faith, of God working in my life, of blessing that I have repeatedly gone back to when doubts have come. I knew, without a doubt, that God had, for some reason decided to bless me. My father had just died from cancer. I was in a state of shock and doubting. But I firmly believe because of my obedience to study His Word, He rewarded me with that championship. Financially, it was a huge help to my mother. We received 1/4 off tuition scholarship at Houghton College. With the loss of my father's income, it was such a blessing. When I look back on that year of quizzing, I do not remember any joy in winning or a drive to win. Studying was not about that. I was just doing it. And in that, the Holy Spirit filled me with such peace that it really did not matter if we won or lost. What was important was that God directly worked in my life. What was important was that feeling (knowledge) that I was not my own...I was bought at a price...and He was in control....It was bigger, much bigger than winning a competition.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Because of that dramatic way of God showing me He was alive and living in me, I have been forever changed. I decided I wanted all teens to have that chance for God to work in their lives, and it might come through quizzing like it did for me.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How have you been involved in quizzing since you were a quizzer?">
			<answer>So after college and marriage, I started a Free Methodist quiz team in the Yorkshire Free Methodist Church in 1975. I was not aware of any other teams in New York at that time. We did not have anyone to quiz with throughout the year. Needless to say, what innocents or rookies we were as we traveled out to Winona Lake with my 3 month old baby boy, C J, in 1976 to quiz in our first nationals. It did not go too well, but it was a start of a ministry still going on today. At the Albion Free Methodist Church, I again started up a quiz team in 1985 with 4 quizzers and have been coaching ever since. My three children went through quizzing with both C J and Kelly making it to the final six senior teen individuals. Colleen did not like the competitive aspect and would be distraught when eliminating an opposing team but has gone on to be a VISA missionary, first for 3 years in China, and most likely now on to Thailand. I feel ecstatic and assured as my children go anywhere knowing how thoroughly they are grounded in the scriptures! Kelly is now helping out in the Michigan conference as she attends U of M. CJ is ministering in various capacities in Maryland at his church. There is no agony or worry on my part for them losing their faith.....and I hope that is true for each of the quizzers that has come through our ministry. ...that their lives will more reflect the spirit of Christ the more they memorize and study the scriptures and there will no buffeting by the waves of doubt when they experience Christ's working. So, 19 years of teens have come and gone in our ministry and with it, touching lives for Christ, I pray.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I have been Christian education director, VBS teacher, Sunday School teacher (12 years), CLC director and teacher. Now I just concentrate on the Bible Quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Harold Allman" inducted="2004" participated="1965" church="New Brighton Free Methodist Church" city="New Brighton" state="PA" image="h_allman.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Coached the New Brighton, PA quiz team and served as Pittsburgh Conference Directors for over 20 years.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>The many trips with quizzers and time spent just getting to know them.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>I John 3:16-18 always reminds and convicts me that love must be expressed by action.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>As a Conference Director, I was privileged to meet people from all over the country who shared a passion for the Word of God. Hearing the testimonies of both quizzers and adults was an encouragement and reminder of the great work God can perform in ordinary people and how he can use them to advance His Kingdom and His Gospel. I count it a blessing to know former quizzers who are now pastors, missionaries, church leaders, etc. The people not only memorized the Word, but also heeded and obeyed its teaching.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I have served as Delegate to General Conference 2003, Delegate to Pittsburgh annual conference for many years, and Secretary of local board of administration. I also teach an adult Sunday School class and participate on the praise and worship team.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Lois Allman" inducted="2004" participated="1965" church="New Brighton Free Methodist Church" city="New Brighton" state="PA" image="l_allman.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>Coached the New Brighton, PA quiz team and served as Pittsburgh Conference Directors for over 20 years.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Highlights for me included taking teams to Nationals and just the week-to-week adventure of coaching a team and working with the youth. I enjoyed interpreting the scripture to many teens, some of which had no former training in the scriptures, and to see their hearts and minds change. Watching our own children quiz and staying up late to hear them quote chapters was one of my fondest memories.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Hebrews 12:2-3 was my favorite because keeping my eyes fixed on Jesus has been so important in helping me keep focused in the challenges of ministry and life in general.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>These years of ministry in quizzing have helped me to love God's Word and to desire to share the reality of Christ in my life with others. To see the lives of teenagers changed and to watch leaders emerge has been more rewarding than I can express.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I serve as Adult Ministries Director, member of praise team, children's teacher in midweek, member of leadership team, officer in WMI, and the Pittsburgh Conference Missions Coordinator</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Stanley Thompson" inducted="2004" participated="1957-1959" church="Harvey Free Methodist Church" city="Harvey" state="IL" image="s_thompson.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1958 - International Champions over Genesis</answer>
			<answer>My father, W. Ralph Thompson, was the pastor and also our team's coach. My brother, Carl, and I were both on the championship team in 1958, along with James Setty and Sharon Krantz. The Harvey Free Methodist Church has since relocated to Monee, Illinois.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>A crucial verse in Genesis is Genesis 1:1: "In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth." Genesis, for me, is one of the most interesting and readable books in the Bible. The stories themselves are fascinating--e.g. Adam, Noah, Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, and Joseph. These are stories about real people, real situations. It is easy to relate to their emotions and experiences. It gives a background for some of what is happening in the Middle East today. Beyond that, Genesis tells the story of creation. This responds to one of man's most basic questions: where did I come from?</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Besides being active in quizzing, and about that same time, I was also a member of an Illinois sweet sixteen basketball team from Thornton Township High school. The Free Methodist Church, through quizzing, gave me (and many others) the opportunity to improve myself and excel in a challenging arena equally as absorbing and exciting as any sports or academic competition. In addition, due to the many hours of disciplined study that is required for tournament success, quizzing taught me some valuable study habits and life lessons and reinforced my appreciation for learning. My brother and I both went on to achieve earned doctorates, for example, and I am aware that several quizzers from my era did similarly. Our competition in the finals in 1958 was a very good team from Winona Lake, Indiana--a team which had won the championship the previous year. The three young men who anchored that team, Edward Knox, Dale Martin, and Dale Benson, all went on to achieve doctorates.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How were you involved in quizzer after being a quizzer?">
			<answer>I did wrote the questions one year in the early 70's for the quizzing regionals, semi-finals and finals, and in the 70's I occasionally served as quizmaster for various quizzes.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I retired at the end of 2003 from active service in the Free Methodist Church. Along the way, I was privileged to hold such positions as Assistant Publisher of Light and Light Press, Director of the Division of Planned Giving, President of The Free Methodist Foundation, and Chairman of King Trust Company, NA. I was the founding CEO of the latter three Free Methodist organizations and also was founding Chairman/CEO of King Trust Charitable Gift Fund, the donor advised fund of the Free Methodist Church.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Steve Coates" inducted="2004" participated="1975-1981" church="Moundford Free Methodist Church" city="Decatur" state="IL" image="s_coates.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>National Finals was the highlight of every season. The times of worship and fellowship with quizzers from around the country were a great encouragement in my spiritual development. The annual "Quote-a-thon" was tremendous. Our coach (my brother Chuck) demanded perfection. We had to quote anywhere from 20 to 29 chapters aloud according to his standards of precision. After quoting an entire chapter, he would simply mention the reference of any verse I might have missed. I was given one chance and one chance only to say the verse correctly. If I missed even one letter, I did not receive credit for the verse. His demands resulted in mastery of the material. I also appreciated the great support of our local church for quizzing. We often quoted scripture in worship services and gave quizzing demonstrations to the congregation. The fellowship with teammates at weekly practices and occasional pizza outings formed the basis of my closest friendships throughout high school. </answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Team</answer>
			<answer>1975 - Young Teen National Champion</answer>
			<answer>1976 - Young Teen National Champion</answer>
			<answer>1977 - Young Teen National Champion</answer>
			<answer>1979 - Senior Teen National Champion</answer>
			<answer>1981 - Senior Teen National Champion</answer>
			<answer>Individual</answer>
			<answer>1981 - Senior Teen National Champion</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>One of my favorites was "If I were still trying to please men, I would not be a servant of Christ." (Galatians 1:10) It is so easy to be lured into seeking the approval of persons. As a servant of Christ, I simply want to hear the words "Well done, good and faithful servant" from the mouth of my LORD. Perhaps I was an outstanding quizzer, but as a Christian, I am simply a child of God. If there is a "cream of the crop," I am certainly not in it. I am thankful to be a member of the family of Christ, with brothers and sisters far more talented and gifted than myself. But I have a role to play - we all do. By the grace of God, I will give my very best for Him.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It is impossible for me to quantify the positive impact of quizzing on my life during my teen years. The training of my mind paid tremendous benefits in education. The training of my will saved me from untold pain and suffering resulting from sin. I think I spent nearly 2000 hours memorizing God's Word in my seven years of quizzing. I thank God for the privilege of consuming that much positive input in my mind and for sparing me 2000 hours of potential harm.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>It has been 29 years since I won my first National Championship. I still memorize, and I still quote. Two weeks ago, I quoted nearly 30 minutes of scripture (several hundred verses) as a farewell message for people moving from our congregation. Many of the verses were from quizzing days - others I learned using the same skills and methods I developed decades ago. The Word of God is powerful, and I am so thankful for the discipline of hiding it in my heart that I might not sin against Him.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>After nearly 12 years of pastoral ministry in local Free Methodist churches, I am currently serving as a Chaplain in the United States Navy. My family and I are stationed at Marine Corps Air Station, Iwakuni Japan.</answer>
			<answer>I have coached teams in Greenville (IL), Dearborn (MI), Spring Arbor (MI), Springfield (IL) and now Japan. Praise the LORD for faithful servants who have dedicated themselves to providing direction to this outstanding ministry. It has grown and flourished under their leadership. Once again, I am simply thankful to be associated with such wonderful children of the King.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Alan Noble" inducted="2003" participated="1962-1964" church="Redlands Free Methodist Church" city="Redlands" state="CA" image="a_noble.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Attending the Winona Youth Advance in Winona Lake, IN. This was the 60's version of IYC, and Quiz Finals took place there.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>In 1964, our team placed third in the nation.</answer>
			<answer>I received top quizzer honors in the Southern California Conference in 1962-63 and in 1963-64, and top quizzer at Nationals in 1962-63.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"But sanctify the Lord God in your hearts: and be ready always to give an answer to every man that asketh you a reason of the hope that is in you with meekness and fear:" (I Peter 3:15) This verse has challenged me to share my faith.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It helped to develop my love for God's word.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I continue to memorize scriptures and encourage youth to do the same</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am currently a Bible Quiz coach and Conference Bible Quiz Director. I also service as church treasurer and trustee, and direct the local "Senior Group."</answer>
			<answer>I have been involved in quizzing for over 30 years. During the 80's and 90's my teams had 6 national championships (3 in Senior Teen Veteran), three 2nd place finishes, and several thirds.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Bishop Leslie L. Krober" inducted="2003" participated="1962-1963" church="Greenville Free Methodist Church" city="Greenville" state="IL" image="l_krober.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Teaming up with number 1 quizzers Vickie Jenkins, Carmen Baldwin, and Janice Clem.</answer>
			<answer>I found my wife Peggy through Quizzing; she was on the Spring Abor (MI) team that we beat in the Finals.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Our team won the Championship in 1963. It was a single-elimination tournament and there was only one age category.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>The Sermon on the Mount from Matthew.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It helped me to be disciplined in Bible study.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I still remember and consider the verses I memorized.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I coached the Greenville team two years. We got close to Finals one year and won the championship the other.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I presently serve as Bishop of the Free Methodist Church of North America. </answer>
			<answer>(Editor's Note: Bishop Krober currently serves as the bishop overseeing many denominational ministries including Bible quizzing, and his support and encouragement has been a great blessing to quizzing.)</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Bruce Kaufmann" inducted="2003" participated="1968-1971" church="Greenville Free Methodist Church" city="Greenville" state="IL" image="b_kaufmann.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Winning the National Championship in 1968; all the friends that I made; all the trips that we took; and all the Bible verses that I learned.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1968, 1969, 1970, and 1971 Central Illinois Conference Bible Quiz Champions</answer>
			<answer>1968 Mid-West Regional Bible Quiz Champions, representing Central Illinois at Camp Mack in IN.</answer>
			<answer>1968 National Champions at Winona Lake, IN</answer>
			<answer>Coaching the 1974 National Championship team from Greenville, IL</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>I Corinthians 13. Christ commanded us to "love one another" if we are His disciples. This chapter tells us what love is and is not. I memorized this chapter. Love covers a lot of sin.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Bible quizzing gave me a reason to study God's Word in depth on a regular basis. Bible quizzing was my "sport" of choice. None of the "jocks" on the basketball, baseball, football or track teams ever went to "Nationals" or won an international grand championship title. So it gave me a sense of accomplishment. I learned how to study. I learned how to think under pressure. I learned how to speak in public under pressure, extemporaneously. I learned how to analyze a question and information to determine what my answer would be through reasoning. I learned how to get along with others in tight situations. I learned how to organize information, thoughts, and people. I learned how to consult the Bible for guidance in making "right" decisions in the face of difficult situations.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Bible quizzing has been one of the most influential programs in my life. The lessons that I have learned through Bible quizzing and the Bible verses that I learned have helped me to make "right" decisions in the face of difficult situations. I have had a confidence in myself and my God throughout my life that would not have been there if I did not have the Bible quiz program while I was a teenager. Without this confidence I would not have accomplished the many things that I have. Bible quizzing helped expand my love for God's word which led to my creating, with God's and my brother Don' s help, several Bible educational games and a company to design, manufacture, promote, and sell them.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I am currently coaching a local quiz team at the St. Petersburg (FL) FMC, and have coached national championship teams in the past. I also directed the national Bible Quiz program for many years. </answer>
			<answer>When there was question whether or not Bible quizzing would continue as a denominational ministry, Bruce called together a meeting of lay leaders (who supported Bible Quizzing) at the Wabash Campground in 1973. Bruce proposed a self-supporting organization organizational structure to keep quizzing going. In 1974, as a result of Bruce's encouragement to the Bishops, the Free Methodist International Grand Championships were held in conjunction with the Free Methodist General Conference in order to give Bible quizzing some new exposure. (This was the last time that just conference champions competed.) Fred Thomas became the new Director of Free Methodist Youth Ministries and appointed Bruce to be the FM International Bible Quizmaster. </answer>
			<answer>In 1976, Bruce was able to get the Free Methodist Continental Bible Quiz Finals Open started in Winona Lake, IN at the FM Headquarters. To increase attendance and the number of quizzers who could participate in Finals, this was designed as an "open" tournament for any FM quiz team. Rookie and veteran divisions were started then as well, and this was the first year for the awards banquet. </answer>
			<answer>In 1977, Bruce designed the "Alpha-Omega" Stained Glass Traveling Bible Quiz Trophy and the Open Bible Trophy. The name came from Jesus being the Alpha and Omega. Bruce later created the Spit-Shine Award to encourage team uniforms. </answer>
			<answer>Bruce wrote championship finals questions several years. He served as head Bible quizmaster for many years, and also as Quizmaster for the Florida Conference and the Southeast Regional. He has also won a championship in the QUIC quizzing competition. Bruce has served on the Board of Directors for the World Bible Quiz Association. He also proposed the 8-year Bible quiz study cycle which was adopted by the WBQA and is still being used today.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am a member of the St. Petersburg (FL) FMC, and coach the Bible quiz team. I lead the Divorce Care ministry of our local church, and am on the Men's Ministries leadership team as well as the Mission's Committee. I serve as the attorney for Free Methodist Churches in the South Atlantic Conference. I am also a Gideon.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Dave Markell" inducted="2003" participated="none" church="Free Methodist World Headquarters" city="Indianapolis" state="IN" image="d_markell.jpg">
		<qa question="bio">
			<answer>(Heaven)</answer>
			<answer>The following comes from a letter from his widow, Judi Markell:</answer>
			<answer>David was a man of great faith and a man of the Word. He was up early every morning spending time in prayer and reading scripture to prepare for the day. Every so often, he would set aside an entire day to pray and meditate on the Word. He continually sought God's guidance in every area of his life and recognized the importance of God's Word in the life of every believer.</answer>
			<answer>David also had a heart for youth. He started working with them when he was in college as the youth pastor at the church that sits on this campus at Roberts Wesleyan College. He continued in seminary as a Campus Life director for three years. When he took his first church, he also served his local conference as director of youth. In 1977 he was asked to serve as Director of Youth Ministries for the Free Methodist denomination. While at headquarters, David became acquainted with the Bible quizzing program. It had been in existence for several years, but was not very active at the time. He recognized the potential for the program and the impact it could have on so many kids, so he got to work. It became a burning desire of his to get the word of God into the hearts and minds of the youth of the denomination. He also recognized the importance of other aspects of the program, including learning teamwork, discipline and working toward a common goal.</answer>
			<answer>It was always such a pleasure to watch him work. Whether he was tending to the details of a given meet, trying to get stubborn seats to light up properly, working with coaches, mediating a challenge or quizmastering, he did it all with style, grace and fairness. And all of this was bathed in a great deal of prayer. He worked hard and was able to see the fruits of his labor as the program grew and flourished. It became more personal when he saw his own son become a very enthusiastic quizzer. I know he was equally as thrilled when, watching from his heavenly home, he saw his daughter become involved in the program. </answer>
			<answer>The program is bigger and better than ever. It is due, in part, to what David did, but it also is due to what a lot of others, such as Mike Hopper, have done. And I know David would absolutely want me to give Jesus Christ all the praise for what the program has become. The bottom line is what David knew to be Truth- once the Word gets in your mind and heart, it will never leave. Thank you for the honor you have bestowed on David. I know he is smiling down from heaven this day.</answer>
			<answer>It is good to know he is not forgotten. May God bless all of you richly as you continue your good work in this invaluable endeavor and may His name be glorified today and in all the years ahead as this program continues. </answer>
			<answer>Thank you!</answer>
			<answer>Judi, Kristen and Matt Markell</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Dennis Charles" inducted="2003" participated="1969, 1973-1974" church="Aldersgate Free Methodist Church" city="Indianapolis" state="IN" image="d_charles.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1974 Wabash conference championship. Nationals were by invitation only; we went to Nationals, but did not place.</answer>
			<answer>2nd place individual scoring in the Wabash Conference</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"And we, who with unveiled faces all reflect the Lord's glory, are being transformed into His likeness with ever increasing glory, which comes from the Lord, who is the Spirit." (2 Corinthians 3:18)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing affected my life as a teen by providing me with a tool for discipleship in my life. In school, I was just an average student and never saw myself studying unless I had too. I decided to give Jesus control of my life in high school, and in doing so, desired to find direction through His word. I would read and apply the Word to my life. Soon answering questions became easy. We ended up winning conference finals and that was unthinkable for me. I believe that God was showing me that He could do whatever He wanted with me even though I felt I would not be able to accomplish it. I decided that quizzing was a special ministry and that God could use me in it. I approach quizzing differently than some. The competition to win does not drive me as much as seeing and learning how God chooses to use us through the competition.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Quizzing has affected my life today by having my family exposed to the Christian young people involved. My children have been around quizzing all their lives. They have seen all the role models that have gone through quizzing and can see what people can be like with God's help-not the way the world would like for them to believe. National Finals have been on the family schedule for the last 16 years because I want my family exposed to the exceptional type of teen that comes through the program.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Quizzing has been and is currently my ministry. In the past, I have served as youth director in my local church.</answer>
			<answer>I am presently serving as the Mid-East Regional Director and a local quiz coach at the Indianapolis (Aldersgate) Church. I have also served as Wabash Conference Director.</answer>
			<answer>(Editorial Note: "I don't know of anyone who has served the quizzing ministry with more of a heart for kids and the Lord's work than Dennis. He has selflessly directed a division at Quiz Finals for many years and always helped us keep the spirit of quizzing what it should be. He has served as conference director and regional director for about 15 years and made significant contributions over those years.")</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Donald Kaufmann" inducted="2003" participated="1967-1974" church="Greenville Free Methodist Church" city="Greenville" state="IL" image="d_kaufmann.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Our team was in the Finals 5 of the 7 years I quizzed.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1968 - 1st - Senior Teen Veteran</answer>
			<answer>1971 - 2nd - Senior Teen Veteran</answer>
			<answer>1972 - 2nd - Senior Teen Veteran</answer>
			<answer>1973 - 1st - Senior Teen Veteran</answer>
			<answer>1974 - 1st - Senior Teen Veteran</answer>
			<answer>Member of the All-Star Team in 1970</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Seek ye first the kingdom of God and His righteousness, and all these things will be added unto you." (Matthew 6:33) I have taken this as the desire of my life-to seek to do God's will above anything else.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Bible Quizzing allowed me to study the Bible. I also put a lot of scripture in my mind which has helped me grow spiritually and as a pastor even today.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>My knowledge of Scripture gained through Bible quizzing has helped me to live the Christian life and to teach others how to live their lives for God as well</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How have you stayed active in quizzing?">
			<answer>I wrote quiz questions for National Finals for 20 years. I have been a quiz coach, quizmaster, conference, and regional director.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am pastor of the Good Shepherd Free Methodist Church in Kissimmee, FL and also serve as Regional Bible Quiz Director for the southeastern part of the United States.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Eric Young" inducted="2003" participated="1988-1991" church="Pearce Memorial Free Methodist Church" city="North Chili" state="NY" image="e_young.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>The biggest highlight my first year of quizzing was our trip to Seattle, WA for nationals at Seattle Pacific University. Flying on a 747 from Newark, NJ for the first time was a thrill. Our trips to the Space Needle and the ferry ride to Bremerton for ice cream were great! Who could ever forget the HUGE water balloon fight on the hill between the residents of Ashton and Hill Halls? The Winona Lake, IN tournament was always a highlight for us. I could not tell you who owned the home, but every year our team was invited to take over this couple's house while they vacationed. One year there was an ice storm and we were forced to cram everyone into one van and leave the others behind with our gear somewhere in Ohio. Our team would also have a retreat on the first weekend of June at RWC's Davis Mountain. We would spend time growing closer as a team and of course, studying! These were always great times together. At the end of our season we would also have a banquet to award and recognize all of the quizzers. Our coaches would come up with these absurd awards for us. I recall earning the Navigator Award for my skill in getting us around Seattle and the Un-bonding Award, a take on Donald Joy's classic book for my many crushes. Most importantly were the relationships our coaches had with us. They always took a genuine interest in our lives and we had many times of prayer together where we would bare our souls and there would not be a dry eye in the house. I particularly recall one Sunday when one our quizzers broke down over the impending divorce of her parents. I know I recall that specific time because it rang true to my situation that I was also in at the time. My head coach became my second mom and helped guide me through many difficult times in my life.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Our STV team was the Genesee Conference champs in 1989, 1990 and 1991. I was the STV Individual Champion for the Genesee Conference in 1990. I was a part of the Genesee Superkwik QUIC team in 1998 that took 2nd at Nationals (Spring Arbor). I finished 5th for QUIC Individuals in 1998 at Nationals (Spring Arbor). Best Balanced Team, 1989 Nationals at Seattle Pacific University; Spit Shine Award, 1990 Nationals at Roberts Wesleyan College</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>The one Scripture that I came to cling to as a teen was Romans 15:13, "May the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace as you trust in Him, so that you may overflow with hope by the power of the Holy Spirit." Although my motivations for quizzing were not what most coaches want to hear, I did try to place my trust in Him. My life was anything but full of joy and peace. Constant struggles at home did not place much hope in my life. It was only from my own decision to place my trust in the Lord that there was any glimmer of hope for my life. </answer>
			<answer>Today I view 2 Corinthians 12:9a as my favorite Scripture, "But he said to me, 'My grace is sufficient for you, for My power is made perfect in weakness.'" It was in retrospect that I realized that it was only by the grace of God that I was saved. It was in the weakest times of my life when the Lord was able to work in me the most. It was in those times when I relinquished control that the Lord was able to step in and carry me. This promise of Scripture has been one I have come back to many times over the years. I have had many thorns in my flesh, but the Lord has always been faithful. For when I am weak, then I am strong!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Growing up I found myself being torn apart by parents who were divorced and the spouses that they remarried. I took refuge in the church, but more importantly I took refuge in the youth group. I did not want to be home, so any opportunity that I had to get out of the house, I did. This was the primary motivation I had when I started quizzing. I also was big into sports and was a top swimmer at my school and the league that we were in. In the summer after my freshman year, I hurt my back and it required surgery. I was no longer able to compete. Quizzing was an outlet for my competitive spirit. I liked to win, and I studied to win. </answer>
			<answer>My ability to quote Scripture quickly and at opportune times did not win me any points with my peers at school. Despite my motivations, I tried to do well. I tried to build up those who were weak. I found myself in trouble at times with teachers and the principal because of my beliefs. It was a way for me to stand out at school, a way to be noticed. </answer>
			<answer>The biggest affect on me as a teen was the fact that I found a family outside of my home that loved me and cared for me. My coaches were of great support to me. Debbie Sommerville, our head coach, was my second mom. As a teen, quizzing was a way to escape and a way for me to feel important because of how I performed. As a teen, the Word was committed to my memory. Only later, once I was in college, did the Word make a permanent 10-inch move from my head and into my heart.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>The Word of God tells us that His Word will not return void. This promise was fulfilled in my life. While motivations for quizzing were purely competitive for me as a teen, the Word that I had committed to memory began to work in my life. In college I found myself caught up in the world of smoking and alcohol. It took hitting rock bottom for me to be shaken. One morning I found myself on the streets of Buffalo, wet from the rain and unclear on what happened that night. It was then when I cried out to God, "There has to be more to my life than this! I am tired of chasing after things that only hurt me!" It was time to stop just listening to Word; it was time to do what it said. </answer>
			<answer>The Lord began to work and the Word that I had memorized found residence in my heart. Through the help and support of friends, I was back on my feet. It was then that the Lord began to tug at my heart. He was calling me to His ministry; and in an effort to run and leave my past behind me, I enrolled at Roberts Wesleyan College to study Religion and Philosophy. If it wasn't for the work that I had put in for quizzing, the committing of his Word to my memory, it would have never been available to me when I needed it most. His Word did not return void in my life. It profoundly changed me. </answer>
			<answer>Quizzing continues to make a difference in my life even today. I provide leadership for quizzing because it is my way of giving back to the program that helped save me. It is a way for me to have a positive influence on teens, in an effort to help them avert the path that I took- the hard one. Many coaches have differing philosophies on how to lead a team. For me, I realize that quizzing is not for everyone, but I have made an effort to make it that way. Whether a quizzer is putting in 100% effort or only 10% effort, they are opening the Word of God. Teens are being exposed to His Word. Teens are being shown an example by their coaches as to what it means to lead godly lives. Quite frankly, some teens just need the interaction. They need to be around peers and out of their homes. I would much rather have a teen giving 10% with me at a tournament on a Saturday than left behind to get drawn into worldly things. I cannot think of a better way for teen to spend a Saturday than quizzing over His Word. </answer>
			<answer>It is a privilege to be a part of a teen's spiritual journey. It is so amazing to see a teen come into the quizzing program in 6th grade and to watch him or her mature over the years. To be able to stand with them at graduation and to know that you had a profound impact on how they will continue on in life is quite overwhelming.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I am presently the Northeast Regional Director and the Genesee/Susquehanna Conference Director for FMC Bible quizzing. I have served in these roles for the past 4 and 5 years, respectively. I am also working with Mike Hopper this year as a co-director of the National tournament at RWC. I have also served as a coach for the start-up team at New Hope FMC in the city of Rochester, NY. Prior to coaching at New Hope I served as the head coach of the Pearce Memorial FMC in North Chili, NY for 3 years. While in college, I attended quiz tournaments as a quizmaster.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Currently I am an Associate Pastor at the Gowanda, NY FMC working full-time with youth. Our youth group, called YES Inc. (Youth Equipped to Serve in the Name of Christ), is very active in our community and is committed to growing in their relationships with God and with each other. </answer>
			<answer>In Gowanda youth leaders from Assembly of God Church and Youth for Christ are partnering with us to pursue a Youth Center. I also serve on the Board of Directors for LOVE InC of the Greater Gowanda Area. For people in need and those wanting to help them, LOVE InC is an answer to prayer. I continue to serve the Bible quizzing ministry giving leadership to our local quiz team and to the Northeast Region of Conferences. There are 3 conferences in our region that do not have quiz teams and we pray for leaders who will rise up and be willing to promote quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Gerald Coates" inducted="2003" participated="1975-1979" church="Moundford Free Methodist Church" city="Decatur" state="IL" image="g_coates.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Quizzing in Estes Park, CO in 1975, and winning the National Championship in 1977.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>1977 - Senior Teen National Champion</answer>
			<answer>1979 - Senior Teen National Champion</answer>
			<answer>Our team received the Best-Balanced Team Award in 1977.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrel against any: even as Christ forgave you, so also do ye." Colossians 3:13 sets the standard for forgiveness.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I made lots of friends and implanted the scripture in my mind.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I am still recalling scripture by memory that I learned over 20 years ago.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I have pastored in the Free Methodist denomination for 16 years, and currently serve as Administrator for Free Methodist Communications.</answer>
			<answer>I have continued to be active in quizzing through coaching and quizmastering.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Herb W. Coates" inducted="2003" participated="1975, 1977" church="Moundford Free Methodist Church" city="Decatur" state="IL" image="h_coates.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Learning God's word and winning the competitions were highlights for me.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Our team was the first winner/recipient of the Alpha-Omega Trophy when we won the national championship in the Senior Teen Veteran Division in 1977. I was on the All-Star Team of 1975 and 1977.</answer>
			<answer>Top quizzer in the Central Illinois Conference in 1975 and 1977. Our team won the Best-Balanced Award at Nationals in 1977.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"I am crucified with Christ: nevertheless I live; yet not I, but Christ liveth in me: and the life which I now live in the flesh I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave Himself for me." Galatians 2:20 is my life verse.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing was the greatest means of discipling me in the Word.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I am never away from God's Word. Even though I don't have the Bible with me at all times, I always have large portions of it in me for the Holy Spirit to bring to my mind.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I presently serve as senior pastor of the Vincennes (IN) Free Methodist Church.</answer>
			<answer>I served as a coach for Springfield, IL for ten years. Currently I am simply a strong supporter as we have very competent coaches in our church in Vincennes, IN.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Iona Sewell" inducted="2003" participated="1958-1963" church="Columbus First Free Methodist Church" city="Columbus" state="IN" image="i_sewell.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Meeting wonderful people; having those "ahha" moments when the scripture begins to make sense and come together; taking trips; making life-long friends; growing as a Christian; and my coach!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>We never won any conference championships because that was when the "Benson Dynasty" from Winona Lake was in effect in the Wabash Conference. They were always the winners! Our team did, however, win many quizzes.</answer>
			<answer>I received several trophies. One of the wonderful things that my coach's husband did for me was to make them into bookends for me as I went to college.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>There are so many: John 1:1-14; I Corinthians 13 and 10:13; John 8 (the story of the woman caught in adultery); Matthew 5-7 (Sermon on the Mount); John 14; and the Book of Luke. The reasons these scriptures are so important to me are because of how they've come back to me over and over again right when I needed them-I never forgot them.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Bible Quizzing for me became the avenue through which I realized what Christ desired of my life. Since I was not born into a Christian home and did not attend church until the 5th grade, I knew nothing of what the Bible said about needing a Savior or of walking with Christ after salvation. Learning the scriptures in Bible quizzing opened up an entire new life of trusting myself daily to a Friend that loved me more than any of my family, communicating constantly with Someone who understood me completely, growing more deeply committed each day to following His wonderful plan for my life, and seeing that no matter what I went through in my life, He was constantly by my side. </answer>
			<answer>Bible Quizzing helped me establish a regular time of reading, studying, and memorizing the Word to find guidance for my daily walk with Christ. My Bible quiz coach became more than a friend to me. She became my mentor and second parent who greatly challenged and influenced me to be all that Christ wanted me to be-a better student and one who practiced the gifts God had given me to better serve Him-and she gave me the vision to believe that I could go to college and excel-something no one in my family had ever done!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Bible quizzing began a quest for learning the truth about everything..creation, how to identify godly and ungodly characteristic in myself and others, "tying in" all of scripture to get a complete picture of God at work, who Jesus is and how He is the complete picture of God at work, who Jesus is and how He is the complete representation of who God is, discovering how archeology and historical events support the stories of the Bible, and learning how to apply the words of scripture to my life daily. </answer>
			<answer>Several scriptures that I memorized as a teenager have come back to me again and again as an adult at the exact moment I needed them. I Corinthians 10:13 has encouraged me so many times when I was being tempted; John 14 has been such an encouragement to me, especially when my sister and mother died. I've never feared dying because I know that my Heavenly Father has a place prepared just for me. The Book of Romans has helped me as I've endeavored to lead individuals to Christ by knowing the "Roman Road" scriptures. As a Sunday School teacher for many years for children and teens, I've retold and acted out the parables, miracles, stories I learned as a quizzer to excite my students toward living for Christ. When my children became old enough to quiz, I became a quizmaster so that I could continue to participate in the Bible Quiz program. </answer>
			<answer>The best thing that quizzing has done for me is that it's given me a real love for God's word in my life. As I've seen the living Word, Jesus, work in my life over the years, I've been reminded again and again how He has worked through His word to bring about His will for myself and my family. One example of this is that several years ago, I felt the Lord impressing upon me to memorize a meaningful passage when anything significant happened in my life. So, I began to do this. As my mother and father-in-law died in the 1980's, I memorized some chapters in the Old Testament. When my son was diagnosed with cancer, I memorized a psalm and so on. It's proven to be an exercise that has blessed and enriched me more than anything else.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I teach Sunday School, and we take our lessons right from the Bible. I serve on the local Mercy Committee, and coach the quiz team. I also serve on the Conference Historical Committee, the MEG Board and the MAC for the Wabash Conference, and am the delegate for the Columbus (IN) FMC. I am also a General Conference delegate.</answer>
			<answer>I am currently a coach. I've quizmastered over the years when my children were teens and involved in Bible Quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="James P. Kramer" inducted="2003" participated="1988-1996" church="Willamina Free Methodist Church" city="Willamina" state="OR" image="j_kramer.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Even to this day, I keep in contact with friends I made during my quizzing years. I even ended up being roommates at George Fox University with one of my fiercest competitors. The friendships I've made from quizzing have been amazing. The scriptures I memorized didn't always carry meaning right away. But over time, as I've encountered different things, God has reminded me of certain scriptures I either didn't understand at the time, or else neglected to pay attention to. But God has been faithful to teach me His Word and to remind me of things I memorized years ago. I enjoyed traveling around the country and having a good God-centered competition with people that lifted up and encouraged one another. The competition was tough, but the people were always great, and I usually left tournaments feeling better as a person regardless of who won. I learned team unity and I learned to give grace to others. Sometimes I won, sometimes I lost - and I learned how to be graceful in both.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>STV 1st Place at Nationals - Spring Arbor</answer>
			<answer>STV 2nd Place at Nationals - Greenville</answer>
			<answer>STV 3rd Place at Nationals - Greenville</answer>
			<answer>STV 3rd Place at Nationals - Anderson</answer>
			<answer>STV 4th Place at Nationals - Warm Beach</answer>
			<answer>Various Regional Competition - 1st, 2nd Finishes</answer>
			<answer>Individuals:</answer>
			<answer>YTV 1st Place at Nationals - Greenville</answer>
			<answer>YTV 4th Place at Nationals - Spring Arbor</answer>
			<answer>STV 1st Place at Nationals - Warm Beach</answer>
			<answer>STV 3rd Place at Nationals - Greenville</answer>
			<answer>Various Regional Competition -1st, 2nd, 3rd Finishes</answer>
			<answer>1996 - Dave Markell Excellence in Attitude Award</answer>
			<answer>Most Inspirational Team (can't remember the year) Quote Award - every year</answer>
			<answer>Nominated for Most Inspirational Quizzer (PNW Conference) - 4 years</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Without a doubt it is Philippians 1:6 - "He who began a good work in you will carry it on to completion until the day of Christ Jesus." I can see God's hand in my life over and over again, highlighting areas that need work, using His refining touch to break up the hard soil and remove roots of sin from my heart. At times I'm tempted to despair, wondering if I'll ever change, if I'll ever be the new creation that Paul talks about. But when I go to prayer, God reminds me that He is pleased with me and that He is doing His work and He will finish it. Time and time again I'm humbled by God's consistent, faithful, fatherly love that won't let me get too far before He gently lifts me up in His arms and tells me to cease my striving. As I've come to trust His work in my life, I've also been able to tell others about this indescribable love I've received. And in so doing, I've been able to see Christ doing His redeeming work in other lives as well. This is truly a Gospel of liberation and freedom</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It was by far the most positive influence I had. I was surrounded by God-loving friends that I enjoyed being with. I had an identity in quizzing. I did not feel the need to do what my non-Christian friends were doing, because I was finding pleasure in quizzing and in learning more about God. I think quizzing provided a shelter from the things of the world that might have tried to win me over. Nothing in my life has compared with my years in quizzing.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Time and again when I'm faced with difficulties or confusions or crises, God brings to mind scriptures I learned as a teen. He not only reminds me of them, but He brings them to life and gives them meaning. I know the scriptures better than many of my friends and so He also uses me to teach them about Himself when they are going through tough times. I learned important life lessons from quizzing that I have carried with me to this day. For one, I learned how to study and discipline myself. I learned how to work hard towards a goal. I learned how to work together as a team and put self-interests to rest. I learned how to give grace and receive grace. I learned how to compete in a Godly way that still allows for fierce competition and fun, but also includes love and encouragement.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>This last fall, I was on staff at a Christian discipleship school in Oregon (based on the YWAM model). Just this week, I returned from 3 months of outreach and evangelism in Mexico with the school. Before that, I taught at a University in China for a year, holding Bible studies in my apartment and discipling many new Christians and people interested in things of God. This fall, I will be on staff at the school once again, but I will be directing most of my attention to the creation of a new aspect of the school. I will be the director of a one-month Intensive Missions Training Boot Camp to be held this spring in Mexico. This will be geared towards preparing young people from all denominations for missions life and work.</answer>
			<answer>I am currently coaching a STV team for Willamina. I also coached one year for Greenville.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Laura Christensen Colberg" inducted="2003" participated="1982-1988" church="Wenatchee Free Methodist Church" city="Wenatchee" state="WA" image="l_colberg.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Maintaining friendships and getting reacquainted with competitors year after year. I also helped start the water fight tradition at Nationals.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Team</answer>
			<answer>1984 - 1st - Young Teen Veteran</answer>
			<answer>1987 - 1st - Senior Teen Veteran</answer>
			<answer>Individual</answer>
			<answer>1988 - 1st - Senior Teen Veteran</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Consider it pure joy, my brothers, whenever you face trials of many kinds, because you know that the testing of your faith develops perseverance. Perseverance must finish its work so that you may be mature and complete, not lacking anything." James 1:2-4 is a constant reminder that growth can and often is unpleasant, but that character and maturity come from facing various trials and learning from each one.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It gave me a place to grow in self-confidence and succeed, and to become rooted in my faith. It laid the foundation for my love of Scripture and for my passion to ignite that same spark in other youth.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>others in the life God desires for us.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>Following graduation from high school, I coached a quiz team at the Ballard (WA) FMC from 1989-1993. I quizmastered and started writing practice materials 1994-1998, and began coaching at the Shoreline (WA) FMC in 1999. I started writing the denominational tournament questions in 2000.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I'm on the leadership team for Professional Women's Fellowship, a non-denominational ministry in the Seattle area which addresses the spiritual needs of working women. I'm on the Board of Administration at the Shoreline (WA) FMC and oversee the quiz program at Shoreline.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Lynette Sittig Sykora" inducted="2003" participated="1987-1993" church="Pearce Memorial Free Methodist Church" city="North Chili" state="NY" image="l_sykora.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>My 8th grade year, when Nationals was at SPU (1989) my YTV team won 3rd place. My 9th grade year, when Nationals was at Greenville, my STR team won 3rd place. My 10th grade year, when Nationals was at Central College, my STV team won 4th place Watching my brother win STV Individual Finals at Nationals in 1991. I won individual competition in all categories in our Conference or in the region.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"Come to Me, all you who are weary and burdened, and I will give you rest. Take My yoke upon you and learn from Me, for I am gentle and humble in heart, and you will find rest for your souls. For My yoke is easy and my burden is light." (Matthew 11:28-30) The year my mom died, this scripture spoke to me about rest and comfort in the Lord. (I also was very proud our team memorized the genealogy in Matthew.)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It gave me great motivation to learn the Bible. It also provided a wonderful group of people with whom to learn, compete, and grow. I cherish those days.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Having so much Scripture memorized or at least familiarized helped me in studying generally, and in studying the Bible. It also helped me when I had to teach in Hungarian. I was quicker to know the reference and tell it to others in Hungarian. It has taught me what is possible for our minds!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I helped coach teams at Pearce Memorial FMC and at Park Ridge FMC. We have demonstrated quizzing in Hungary, and used the format for one of our English classes to test basic knowledge.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I have been a FM missionary since 1998 (through to the present) in Hungary/Europe. We have been church planting, and I also led a youth group.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Mark Colgan" inducted="2003" participated="1977-1980" church="New Castle Fee Methodist Church" city="New Castle" state="IN" image="m_colgan.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>My wife Kathy and I quizzed together as teens. My dad was our coach, and we enjoyed a lot of good family time. We had fun quizzing at Winona Lake for National Quiz Finals and going out for ice cream or pizza when we won quizzes. Rick Gensch was a young quizzer who not only quizzed well but also made things fun and interesting. Some of the quizzers we enjoyed quizzing against were Mike Hopper, Greg Sanders, Steve Coates and Gerry Coates.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Team</answer>
			<answer>1980 - 1st - Senior Teen Veteran</answer>
			<answer>Individual</answer>
			<answer>1980 - 1st - Senior Teen Veteran</answer>
			<answer>In 1978 at Quiz Finals I was on the All-star team with Mike and Nancy Hopper and Greg Sanders.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>While quizzing over the Book of Acts, I really liked Acts 20:24: "However, I consider my life worth nothing to me, if only I may finish the race and complete the task the Lord Jesus has given me, the task of testifying to the gospel of God's grace." I liked the racing analogy Luke used because I always enjoyed sports and could identify with finishing the race. I felt like my life would only be a success if I could finish what God gave me to do.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Bible quizzing gave me a foundation in the Scripture that changed my way of thinking by "the renewing of [my] mind" (Romans 12:2). I came to understand that all of life can be interpreted through the message of the Bible. Quizzing helped me grow in my faith year by year by constantly studying and memorizing the Word.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I still enjoy memorizing passages for QUIC quizzing and again experience the power of memorizing the Word and how the Spirit speaks in special ways when we memorize. When I hear statements made, I often think of how that fits or doesn't fit with various Bible passages. Quizzing has forever changed my way of thinking by helping me focus on what the Bible says about life. The discipline I learned through quizzing continues to help me in my walk with the Lord.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>My wife and I started coaching a quiz team at the North Anderson (IN) Church while we were students in college in 1982. A great quizzing highlight for us was coaching our team in 1985 at IYC in Colorado. When we moved to Bedford, Indiana, I had the opportunity to coach there for 6 years with Jerry Mullis and many other fine coaches and quizzers. Since 1991, I have enjoyed coaching the Anderson Wesley team. I have also served as the Mid-East Regional Director and as the national Co-Director with Mike Hopper.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am currently a mathematics teacher and department chair at Taylor University in Upland, Indiana. Taylor is a liberal arts Christian college where I have many opportunities to serve students and faculty. Once each week I share a Bible memory verse with my students involving mathematics, and I encourage them to memorize the verses for extra credit. My experience with Bible quizzing has certainly touched every area of my life!</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Paul Stackhouse" inducted="2003" participated="1979-1981" church="Oakdale Free Methodist Church" city="Jackson" state="KY" image="p_stackhouse.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>Learning and memorizing scripture. Attending nationals at Greenville College and Spring Arbor College.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Our team placed third nationally and won several firsts and seconds in Wabash Conference quizzing in level A and B. I came in 5th in individuals over Acts in 1981,	I was awarded a sportsmanship award from our local coach, Rev. C. E. Odermann</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>"My prayer is not for them alone. I pray also for those who will believe in Me through their message, that all of them may be one, Father, just as You are in Me and I am in You. May they also be in us so that the world may believe that You have sent Me." In John 17:20-21 Jesus prayed for all of us who are believers now.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>Quizzing solidified much of the life-changing work of Jesus Christ in my life as a teen.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>Scripture I memorized as a teen remains alive and active in my life nearly every day!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I continue to serve as Free Methodist Denominational Statistician and Webmaster. The local FM churches here don't offer quizzing; I am an active coach in the Ohio Valley District of the C&amp;MA church with whom my daughter just finished quizzing as a junior (5th grade) quizzer.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I have just finished my third term as a lay elder in our local church. I serve as the volunteer network administrator for our church (12 PCs). I am a weekly adult leader in our church's children's ministry called "Exploration Station". I am a greeter in regular rotation and serve as a small group leader. </answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Scott Sittig" inducted="2003" participated="1987-1989, 1991" church="Pearce Memorial Free Methodist Church" city="North Chili" state="NY" image="s_sittig.jpg">
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Senior Teen Individual Championship at Nationals in 1991</answer>
			<answer>The closest my team came was 4th in 1989.1</answer>
			<answer>Our team won the Spit Shine Award one year, and I won several trophies at the local level.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>So many have come back at necessary times over the years. Some that stand out are: Hebrews 11:6; Matthew 11:28-30; Acts 2; Hebrews 12:1-3; and I Peter 5:6-7. These particular scriptures stand out because they have been the foundation upon which my faith has grown. During very difficult times and circumstances, I found my heart drawn to these verses and they have taken an even deeper meaning through the years.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>It was a wonderful social event. The trips were great as outlets during those years. I made friends for life. I learned and applied the Word, and it still comes back to this day!</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>All the Scripture in my head and heart has profoundly influenced my faith and my walk. Not only has the word been applied to my life, but the opportunity to have it all buried and locked in my heart has given me confidence to proclaim the word to others. There are not many days that go by where I do not recall verses or the experiences of my quizzing years. Bible Quizzing became a foundation for me and something that I promote whenever I get the chance.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I rejuvenated the Park Ridge FMC team in Rochester (NY) before moving to Chicago. Since then, I have not been involved. I am considering starting a team through the Olive Branch Mission in Chicago.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>Currently I serve as a vice-president for Olive Branch Mission in Chicago, IL. I have helped to plant two churches in the area and have helped in expanding OBM overseas into Central Africa.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
	<inductee name="Shannon Mullis Liu" inducted="2003" participated="1987-1993" church="Bedford Free Methodist Church" city="Bedford" state="IN" image="s_mullis.jpg">
		<qa question="What were the highlights of your quizzing years?">
			<answer>The friends I made and fun I had more than the trophies I won. I also remember a very distinct moment at Spring Arbor when God really comforted me after a loss. Oh, and a cross over quiz we won at Nationals my 7th grade year.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Did you or your team win any championships? If so, what and when?">
			<answer>Team</answer>
			<answer>1988 - 1st - Young Teen Rookie</answer>
			<answer>1989 - 1st - Young Teen Vet</answer>
			<answer>1991 - 1st - Senior Teen Vet</answer>
			<answer>Individuals - </answer>
			<answer>1992 - 1st - Senior Teen Vet</answer>
			<answer>1993 - 2nd - Senior Teen Vet</answer>
			<answer>Dave Markell Attitude Award - 1993</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What was your favorite scripture? Why?">
			<answer>Philippians chapter 3 is my favorite because it is a constant reminder of where my hope and worth rests and a comfort because that hope doesn't rest in anything I do, but in what Christ has done. After 19 years of being a follower of Christ, I still struggle with this at times. It is also a beautiful reminder to me to value, strive for, and live for knowing Christ, becoming like Him in his death, as I eagerly await heaven. I believe the book of Philippians was my favorite book I studied. I am pretty sure I could still quote most of it after 11 years.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How did quizzing affect you as a teen?">
			<answer>I believe I had greater self-confidence because of my success in quizzing. I also really enjoyed the healthy outlet for my competitive nature. I am convinced I learned to study better as a result of quizzing. But more than anything, I believe Bible Quizzing enhanced my relationship with Christ. Not only was I learning a lot of God's word, but I would turn to God during attacks of pre-quiz nerves and post-loss sorrows, and it cemented my relationship with Christ and taught me more of what it means to trust.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="What difference has quizzing made in your life to this day?">
			<answer>I can't really define the impact it has had. I believe it was the single most formative "thing" in my spiritual life during my teen years. How would my life be different now without that formation?</answer>
			<answer>I have no idea. However, I can say that the knowledge of God's word that I gained from quizzing has had a tremendous impact on my spiritual life. God's word in a heart bears fruit, and it has born fruit in my life. More than anything else in my life, quizzing gave me a firm foundation and understanding of the Word of God and what it means for it to be living and active in the life of a believer. (And that's a pretty strong statement coming from someone who spent three years in Seminary)</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="Are you presently involved in Bible quizzing in any way? If so, how?">
			<answer>I have quizmastered often and coached teams from Nicholasville, Kentucky and Indianapolis, Indiana (and a team from Bedford, Indiana). I have also shared in some quizzing leadership in Wabash Conference.</answer>
		</qa>
		<qa question="How are you serving the Lord?">
			<answer>I am currently an associate pastor at the West Morris Street FM church in Indianapolis, IN.</answer>
		</qa>
	</inductee>
</hall-of-fame>
