<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<quotes>
	<season id="2024" books="Romans and James" verses="541">
		<month id="1" name="October" material="Romans 1 - 3" verses="92">
			<quote reference="Romans 1:16">For I am not ashamed of the gospel, because it is the power of God that brings salvation to everyone who believes: first to the Jew, then to the Gentile.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 1:17">For in the gospel the righteousness of God is revealed—a righteousness that is by faith from first to last, just as it is written: “The righteous will live by faith.” </quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 1:20">For since the creation of the world God’s invisible qualities—his eternal power and divine nature—have been clearly seen, being understood from what has been made, so that people are without excuse.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 2:1">You, therefore, have no excuse, you who pass judgment on someone else, for at whatever point you judge another, you are condemning yourself, because you who pass judgment do the same things.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 2:9-11">There will be trouble and distress for every human being who does evil: first for the Jew, then for the Gentile; but glory, honor and peace for everyone who does good: first for the Jew, then for the Gentile. For God does not show favoritism.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 2:13">For it is not those who hear the law who are righteous in God’s sight, but it is those who obey the law who will be declared righteous.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 3:22-24">This righteousness is given through faith in Jesus Christ to all who believe. There is no difference between Jew and Gentile, for all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God, and all are justified freely by his grace through the redemption that came by Christ Jesus.</quote>
		</month>
		<month id="2" name="November" material="Romans 4 - 6" verses="69">
			<quote reference="Romans 4:3">What does Scripture say? “Abraham believed God, and it was credited to him as righteousness.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 4:23-24">The words “it was credited to him” were written not for him alone, but also for us, to whom God will credit righteousness—for us who believe in him who raised Jesus our Lord from the dead.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 5:1-2">Therefore, since we have been justified through faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom we have gained access by faith into this grace in which we now stand. And we boast in the hope of the glory of God.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 5:8">But God demonstrates his own love for us in this: While we were still sinners, Christ died for us.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 5:17">For if, by the trespass of the one man, death reigned through that one man, how much more will those who receive God’s abundant provision of grace and of the gift of righteousness reign in life through the one man, Jesus Christ!</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 6:1-2">What shall we say, then? Shall we go on sinning so that grace may increase? 2 By no means! We are those who have died to sin; how can we live in it any longer?</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 6:11">In the same way, count yourselves dead to sin but alive to God in Christ Jesus.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 6:23">For the wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord.</quote>
		</month>
		<month id="3" name="December" material="Romans 7 - 9" verses="97">
			<quote reference="Romans 7:4">So, my brothers and sisters, you also died to the law through the body of Christ, that you might belong to another, to him who was raised from the dead, in order that we might bear fruit for God.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 8:1-2">Therefore, there is now no condemnation for those who are in Christ Jesus, because through Christ Jesus the law of the Spirit who gives life has set you free from the law of sin and death.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 8:16">The Spirit himself testifies with our spirit that we are God’s children.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 8:18">I consider that our present sufferings are not worth comparing with the glory that will be revealed in us.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 8:28">And we know that in all things God works for the good of those who love him, who have been called according to his purpose.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 8:38-39">For I am convinced that neither death nor life, neither angels nor demons, neither the present nor the future, nor any powers, neither height nor depth, nor anything else in all creation, will be able to separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 9:33">As it is written: “See, I lay in Zion a stone that causes people to stumble and a rock that makes them fall, and the one who believes in him will never be put to shame.</quote>
		</month>
		<month id="4" name="January" material="Romans 10 - 12" verses="78">
			<quote reference="Romans 10:12-13">For there is no difference between Jew and Gentile—the same Lord is Lord of all and richly blesses all who call on him, for, “Everyone who calls on the name of the Lord will be saved.”</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 10:17">Consequently, faith comes from hearing the message, and the message is heard through the word about Christ.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 11:36">For from him and through him and for him are all things. To him be the glory forever! Amen.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 12:1">Therefore, I urge you, brothers and sisters, in view of God’s mercy, to offer your bodies as a living sacrifice, holy and pleasing to God—this is your true and proper worship.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 12:2">Do not conform to the pattern of this world, but be transformed by the renewing of your mind. Then you will be able to test and approve what God’s will is—his good, pleasing and perfect will.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 12:9-10">Love must be sincere. Hate what is evil; cling to what is good. Be devoted to one another in love. Honor one another above yourselves.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 12:12">Be joyful in hope, patient in affliction, faithful in prayer.</quote>
		</month>
		<month id="5" name="February" material="Romans 13 - 15" verses="70">
			<quote reference="Romans 13:10">Love does no harm to a neighbor. Therefore love is the fulfillment of the law.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 13:12">The night is nearly over; the day is almost here. So let us put aside the deeds of darkness and put on the armor of light.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 14:8">If we live, we live for the Lord; and if we die, we die for the Lord. So, whether we live or die, we belong to the Lord.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 15:1-2">We who are strong ought to bear with the failings of the weak and not to please ourselves. Each of us should please our neighbors for their good, to build them up.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 15:5-6">May the God who gives endurance and encouragement give you the same attitude of mind toward each other that Christ Jesus had, so that with one mind and one voice you may glorify the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.</quote>
			<quote reference="Romans 15:13">May the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace as you trust in him, so that you may overflow with hope by the power of the Holy Spirit.</quote>
		</month>
		<month id="6" name="March" material="Romans 16, James 1 - 2" verses="80">
			<quote reference="Romans 16:20">The God of peace will soon crush Satan under your feet. The grace of our Lord Jesus be with you.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 1:2-3">Consider it pure joy, my brothers and sisters, whenever you face trials of many kinds, because you know that the testing of your faith produces perseverance.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 1:17">Every good and perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of the heavenly lights, who does not change like shifting shadows.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 1:19-20">My dear brothers and sisters, take note of this: Everyone should be quick to listen, slow to speak and slow to become angry, because human anger does not produce the righteousness that God desires.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 1:22">Do not merely listen to the word, and so deceive yourselves. Do what it says.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 2:12-13">Speak and act as those who are going to be judged by the law that gives freedom, because judgment without mercy will be shown to anyone who has not been merciful. Mercy triumphs over judgment.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 2:26">As the body without the spirit is dead, so faith without deeds is dead.</quote>
		</month>
		<month id="7" name="April" material="James 3 - 5" verses="55">
			<quote reference="James 3:13">Who is wise and understanding among you? Let them show it by their good life, by deeds done in the humility that comes from wisdom.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 3:17">But the wisdom that comes from heaven is first of all pure; then peace-loving, considerate, submissive, full of mercy and good fruit, impartial and sincere.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 4:7-8">Submit yourselves, then, to God. Resist the devil, and he will flee from you. Come near to God and he will come near to you. Wash your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you double-minded.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 4:10">Humble yourselves before the Lord, and he will lift you up.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 5:8">You too, be patient and stand firm, because the Lord’s coming is near.</quote>
			<quote reference="James 5:16">Therefore confess your sins to each other and pray for each other so that you may be healed. The prayer of a righteous person is powerful and effective.</quote>
		</month>
	</season>
</quotes>