<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<quotes>
  <season id="2024" books="Romans and James" verses="541">
	<month id="1" name="October" material="Matthew 14 - 16" verses="100">
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 14:27</reference>
			<verse>But Jesus immediately said to them: “Take courage! It is I. Don’t be afraid.”</verse>
		</quote>
    <quote>
			<reference>Matthew 14:32-33</reference>
			<verse>And when they climbed into the boat, the wind died down. Then those who were in the boat worshiped him, saying, “Truly you are the Son of God.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 15:10-11</reference>
			<verse>Jesus called the crowd to him and said, “Listen and understand. What goes into someone’s mouth does not defile them, but what comes out of their mouth, that is what defiles them.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 16:15-16</reference>
			<verse>“But what about you?” he asked. “Who do you say I am?” Simon Peter answered, “You are the Messiah, the Son of the living God.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 16:24-25</reference>
			<verse>Then Jesus said to his disciples, “Whoever wants to be my disciple must deny themselves and take up their cross and follow me. For whoever wants to save their life will lose it, but whoever loses their life for me will find it.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 16:26</reference>
			<verse>“What good will it be for someone to gain the whole world, yet forfeit their soul? Or what can anyone give in exchange for their soul?”</verse>
		</quote>
	</month>
	<month id="" name="November" material="Matthew 17 - 20:16">
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 17:20</reference>
			<verse>He replied, “Because you have so little faith. Truly I tell you, if you have faith as small as a mustard seed, you can say to this mountain, ‘Move from here to there,’ and it will move. Nothing will be impossible for you.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 18:3-4</reference>
			<verse>And he said: “Truly I tell you, unless you change and become like little children, you will never enter the kingdom of heaven. Therefore, whoever takes the lowly position of this child is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 18:20</reference>
			<verse>“For where two or three gather in my name, there am I with them.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 19:14</reference>
			<verse>Jesus said, “Let the little children come to me, and do not hinder them, for the kingdom of heaven belongs to such as these.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 19:26</reference>
			<verse>Jesus looked at them and said, “With man this is impossible, but with God all things are possible.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 20:16</reference>
			<verse>“So the last will be first, and the first will be last.”</verse>
		</quote>
	</month>
	<month id="" name="December" material="Matthew 20:17 - 22">
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 21:9</reference>
			<verse>The crowds that went ahead of him and those that followed shouted, “Hosanna to the Son of David!” “Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord!” “Hosanna in the highest heaven!”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 21:22</reference>
			<verse>“If you believe, you will receive whatever you ask for in prayer.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 21:42</reference>
			<verse>Jesus said to them, “Have you never read in the Scriptures: ‘The stone the builders rejected has become the cornerstone; the Lord has done this, and it is marvelous in our eyes’?”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 22:14</reference>
			<verse>“For many are invited, but few are chosen.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 22:37-38</reference>
			<verse>Jesus replied: “ ‘Love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your mind.’ This is the first and greatest commandment.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 22:39-40</reference>
			<verse>“And the second is like it: ‘Love your neighbor as yourself.’ All the Law and the Prophets hang on these two commandments.”</verse>
		</quote>
	</month>
	<month id="" name="January" material="Matthew 23 - 24">
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 23:37</reference>
			<verse>“Jerusalem, Jerusalem, you who kill the prophets and stone those sent to you, how often I have longed to gather your children together, as a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, and you were not willing.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 24:12-13</reference>
			<verse>“Because of the increase of wickedness, the love of most will grow cold, but the one who stands firm to the end will be saved.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 24:35</reference>
			<verse>“Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will never pass away.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 24:44</reference>
			<verse>“So you also must be ready, because the Son of Man will come at an hour when you do not expect him.”</verse>
		</quote>
	</month>
	<month id="" name="February" material="Matthew 25 - 26">
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 25:29</reference>
			<verse>“For whoever has will be given more, and they will have an abundance. Whoever does not have, even what they have will be taken from them.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 25:40</reference>
			<verse>“The King will reply, ‘Truly I tell you, whatever you did for one of the least of these brothers and sisters of mine, you did for me.’”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 26:11-12</reference>
			<verse>“The poor you will always have with you, but you will not always have me. When she poured this perfume on my body, she did it to prepare me for burial.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 26:26</reference>
			<verse>While they were eating, Jesus took bread, and when he had given thanks, he broke it and gave it to his disciples, saying, “Take and eat; this is my body.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 26:27-28</reference>
			<verse>Then he took a cup, and when he had given thanks, he gave it to them, saying, “Drink from it, all of you. This is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 26:41</reference>
			<verse>“Watch and pray so that you will not fall into temptation. The spirit is willing, but the flesh is weak.”</verse>
		</quote>
	</month>
	<month id="" name="March" material="Matthew 27 - 1 Thessalonians 2">
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 27:54</reference>
			<verse>When the centurion and those with him who were guarding Jesus saw the earthquake and all that had happened, they were terrified, and exclaimed, “Surely he was the Son of God!”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>Matthew 28:19-20</reference>
			<verse>“Therefore go and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit, and teaching them to obey everything I have commanded you. And surely I am with you always, to the very end of the age.”</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>1 Thessalonians 1:4-5</reference>
			<verse>For we know, brothers and sisters loved by God, that he has chosen you, because our gospel came to you not simply with words but also with power, with the Holy Spirit and deep conviction. You know how we lived among you for your sake.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>1 Thessalonians 2:3-4</reference>
			<verse>For the appeal we make does not spring from error or impure motives, nor are we trying to trick you. On the contrary, we speak as those approved by God to be entrusted with the gospel. We are not trying to please people but God, who tests our hearts.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>1 Thessalonians 2:13</reference>
			<verse>And we also thank God continually because, when you received the word of God, which you heard from us, you accepted it not as a human word, but as it actually is, the word of God, which is indeed at work in you who believe.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>1 Thessalonians 2:19-20</reference>
			<verse>For what is our hope, our joy, or the crown in which we will glory in the presence of our Lord Jesus when he comes? Is it not you? Indeed, you are our glory and joy.</verse>
		</quote>
	</month>
	<month id="" name="April" material="1 Thessalonians 3 - 2 Thessalonians 3">
		<quote>
			<reference>1 Thessalonians 3:13</reference>
			<verse>May he strengthen your hearts so that you will be blameless and holy in the presence of our God and Father when our Lord Jesus comes with all his holy ones.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>1 Thessalonians 4:7</reference>
			<verse>For God did not call us to be impure, but to live a holy life.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>1 Thessalonians 5:9-10</reference>
			<verse>For God did not appoint us to suffer wrath but to receive salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ. He died for us so that, whether we are awake or asleep, we may live together with him.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>1 Thessalonians 5:16-18</reference>
			<verse>Rejoice always, pray continually, give thanks in all circumstances; for this is God’s will for you in Christ Jesus.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>2 Thessalonians 1:11</reference>
			<verse>With this in mind, we constantly pray for you, that our God may make you worthy of his calling, and that by his power he may bring to fruition your every desire for goodness and your every deed prompted by faith.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>2 Thessalonians 2:16-17</reference>
			<verse>May our Lord Jesus Christ himself and God our Father, who loved us and by his grace gave us eternal encouragement and good hope, encourage your hearts and strengthen you in every good deed and word.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>2 Thessalonians 3:3</reference>
			<verse>But the Lord is faithful, and he will strengthen you and protect you from the evil one.</verse>
		</quote>
		<quote>
			<reference>2 Thessalonians 3:13</reference>
			<verse>And as for you, brothers and sisters, never tire of doing what is good.</verse>
		</quote>
	</month>
</season>
</quotes>